<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of confirmation preached in Oxford, at the first visitation of the right reuerend Father in God, Iohn Lord Bishop of Oxford. September, 27. 1619. By Edward Boughen, chaplaine to the Lord Bishop of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Boughen, Edward, 1587?-1660?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849993</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15174</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15174)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 656:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of confirmation preached in Oxford, at the first visitation of the right reuerend Father in God, Iohn Lord Bishop of Oxford. September, 27. 1619. By Edward Boughen, chaplaine to the Lord Bishop of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Boughen, Edward, 1587?-1660?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop, for Elizabeth Adams, and are to be sold at her shop, in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some leaves stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15174:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15174:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF CONFIRMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, PREACHED IN OXFORD, AT THE FIRST Viſitation of the Right reuerend Father in God, <hi>Iohn Lord Biſhop of Oxford.</hi> September, 27. 1619.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Edward Boughen, <hi>Chaplaine to the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Oxford.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Fidem nos neque nobis recentiorem ab aliis conſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam acceptamus: neque ipſi mentis noſtrae faetus aliis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudere audemus: ne humana putentur pietatis verba: ſed quae à patribus edocti ſumus, ea nos interrogantibus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiamus.</hi> 
               <bibl>Baſil. Epiſt. 60. ad Eccleſ. Antioch.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> for <hi>Elizabeth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams,</hi> and are to be ſold at her ſhop, in Pauls Church-yard. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15174:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15174:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN God, <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord Biſhop of Oxford, my very good Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing heretofore (Right Reuerend) preaehed this Sermon at your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips appointment, and ſince enlarged it (by your aduice) with ſome neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie additions; I haue now alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your directions, and by <hi>publike authoritie</hi> committed it to the preſſe, but not without your Lordſhips name; entreating you to vndertake the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of it, which had not <hi>beene,</hi> much leſſe <hi>beene prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,</hi> if it had not receiued encouragement, and life from you. And I the more willingly publiſh it vnder your name, becauſe it is <hi>a doctrine of the ancient, primitiue, and Apoſtolicke Church,</hi> whereof you haue beene a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant defender for many yeares; I doubt not therefore, but you will be now as readie and willing to auouch, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this holy and authenticke doctrine, as you were at firſt to enioyne the Text. If there be any worth in me, or in this Sermon, to you (next vnder God) I owe it; hee
<pb facs="tcp:15174:3"/> then that owes himſelfe, and his little lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng to your Lordſhip, dedicates both himſelfe, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ple labours to whom he owes them; beſeeching God to bleſſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with a long and healthfull life for the good of his Church; and ſo to bleſſe me with his gifts and graces, that I may euer delight in thoſe good and ancient ſteppes, which you long haue trod. In theſe deſires I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips dutifull Chaplaine.</hi> Edward Boughen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15174:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF CONFIRMATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Then layed they their hands on them, and they receiued the Holy Ghoſt. <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 8.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou may (peraduenture) eſteeme this to be no viſitation text, as not ſeruing directly, either <hi>ad informan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi> or <hi>reformandos mores,</hi> to put you in minde of your duties, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe what is amiſſe: but if you ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that there is an holy dutie to be performed by the Biſhop in his trienniall viſitation,<note place="margin">Can. 60.</note> and enioyned him by the Canons of the Church, then will this text be found apt and fit for our meeting: which giues oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to prooue that, which the Canon affirmes: viz.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that <hi>Confirmation is a ſolemne, ancient, and laudable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome in the Church of God, continued from the Apoſtles times to this preſent day:</hi> and (wee hope) it may in part make way to remoue that ſerious complaint,<note place="margin">Hooker Eccleſ. pol. lib. 5. §. 66.</note> which Maiſter <hi>Hooker</hi> made of the <hi>deepe neglect of this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian dutie, almoſt with all thoſe, to whom by right of their place and calling, Confirmation belongs:</hi> which deepe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect hath wrought that ill effect amongſt vs, that <hi>William</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> obſerued in his time, <hi>Quod
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15174:4"/> propter ceſſatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Confirmationis tepiditas grandior eſt in fidelibus, &amp; fidei defenſione,</hi> ſince confirmation grew out of vſe,<note place="margin">Getſon de Exterminat. ſchiſmatis.</note> our zeale waxeth cold, and we are become faint in the defence of our faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherefore that you (my brethren of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) may the better be encouraged, to performe that your dutie of ſeaſoning the yonger ſort of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners with the Principles of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thatt hey may be made fit for that holy <hi>Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitions of hands</hi> by the Biſhop, and worthily partake the fruits thereof, I receiued in charge (from him, who may command) the handling of this poynt, and text; wherein I obſerue theſe parts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Firſt, the <hi>Antiquitie of Confirmation:</hi> it was vſed <hi>ſub ipſis Apoſtolis</hi> in the Apoſtles age: 2. The <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of confirmation, <hi>Apoſtoli,</hi> they were no leſſe then Apoſtles, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. The <hi>Perſons</hi> confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Super illos</hi> vpon them, And who were they? 1. <hi>Samaritans.</hi> 2. <hi>Beleeuing Samaritans.</hi> 3. <hi>Baptized Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</hi> We muſt be <hi>firſt baptized,</hi> and <hi>then confirmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, the forme of confirmation. 1. <hi>Oratio, prayer. They prayed for them,</hi> ver. 15. 2. <hi>Manuum impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio, Impoſition of hands; They layed their hands on them,</hi> as in my text: and hence is it called <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> from the manner of performing it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, the <hi>effect, Et accipiebant ſpiritum ſanctum,</hi> They, the <hi>Samaritans</hi> receiued the holy Ghoſt; which was the gift the Apoſtles prayed for, ver. 15. There they <hi>prayed,</hi> that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> might receiue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and here after <hi>Impoſition of hands they receiue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15174:4"/> the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> they are <hi>confirmed by the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and hence it is na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Confirmation, ab effectu,</hi> from the <hi>effect,</hi> and vertue that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hath.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Begin we with the <hi>Antiquitie</hi> of Confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we deduce from hence: from the <hi>place</hi> (I ſay) and <hi>people</hi> here mentioned, where it was firſt practiſed, euen from the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in Samaria, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are here <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> before the conuerſion of the Gentiles. For next of all to Ieruſalem and Iurie, <hi>Samaria</hi> was to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the glad tidings of the Goſpell, in the bleſſed Sacraments, and religious ceremonies of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7 This was that very order our Sauiour himſelfe preſcribed after his reſurrection, for the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell: and they were the laſt words, thoſe memorable words he ſpake before his aſcenſion. <hi>After the Holy Ghoſt is come vpon you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall be witneſſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>both in Ieruſalem, and in all Iudea, and in Samaria, and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the earth:</hi> ſo that the progreſſe of the Goſpel was to be from Iudea to <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſo to the Gentiles vniuerſally.</p>
            <p n="8">8 And this <hi>diuiſion of the world into Iewes, Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, and Gentiles</hi> (which is there ſet downe ſhortly after that <hi>generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion, Euntes docete omnes gentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> go and teach al nations) was formerly made by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in his <hi>limited commiſsion,</hi> when as yet they were but punies, &amp; not fit for ſo general a licence to preach. <hi>Go not</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>into the way of the Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>and enter not into any citty of the Samaritans, but go rather to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Here that is prohibited by a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15174:5"/> retrograde order of Gentiles, <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and Iewes, which is commanded in a direct order <hi>Act</hi> 1. Iewes, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.8.</note> and Gentiles.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The reaſon why Chriſt ſet downe this order, why he appointed the Apoſtles to preach to the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> in the ſecond place; and not to the Gentiles, but reſerued them for a third worke, was becauſe there was <hi>a greater affinitie betweene the Iew, and the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> both in religion, and in place, then was betweene Iew and Gentile: and therefore they were more eaſie to bee wrought vpon, more likely to receiue the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell from the preaching of the Iewes, at the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing it to the world. I ſay, more likely, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the principles of their Religion,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.48. Ioh. 4.9.</note> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not in regard of their extreme diſlike, and diſv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in affection the one from the other.</p>
            <p n="10">10. For the prouince of <hi>Samaria</hi> was ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by the tribe of Ephraim, and the halfe tribe of Manaſſes, men ſprung from the ſame line, and trayned vp in the ſame religion: but they were rooted out by the Aſſyrians, who after the captiuitie of Aſſyria ſent others to plant a Colonie in that country.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 17.25.</note> Theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were Idolaters, and feared not the god of Iſraell; and yet God ſo wrought for them, that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the true religion. Looke into the ſecond of <hi>Kings</hi> 17. And you ſhall ſee, how the Lord ſent Lyons amongſt them, who ſlew that Idolatrous nation; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon complaint being made to the King of Aſſyria, hee ſent them a Prieſt of the Iewes, who inſtructed them in the wayes of the Lord, and taught them how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15174:5"/> they ought to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re the true God of Iſraell.</p>
            <p n="11">11. From that Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt they receiued the Pentateu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fiue bookes of <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and onely them; but witha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they retained their Idols, and worſhipped their falſe Gods: Moreouer, they were ſtrangely corrupted (as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and S. <hi>Ierome</hi> note) and deepely infected with diuers and dangerous errors by a runne-agate Iew;<note place="margin">Epiphaer. 9. Hieron. cont. Lucifer.</note> and by this meanes they were accounted of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iewes, as heretickes and ſchiſmatickes are eſteemd of amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt Chriſtians: ſo that the very name of a <hi>Samaritan</hi> grew odious and ignominious amongſt the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in ſo much that when they thought moſt to diſgrace Chriſt, they reuiled him by the name of a <hi>Samaritan:</hi> and ſuch was the inteſtine hatred betweene thoſe two nations, that there might be no commerce,<note place="margin">Ioh 4.9.</note> no acquaintance, no entercourſe at al betwixt Iew and <hi>Samaritan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Yet by this meanes, by entertayning the fiue bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they became farre more capable and pliable to receiue the Goſpell, then the Gentiles, who denyed the Pentateuch and all. Being therefore next in place, and not altogether different in manners and religion, our Sauiour tooke order, that next to the Iewes the Goſpell ſhould be preached to theſe <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> who receiued it more readily, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully then the Iewes themſelues,<note place="margin">Act. 1.8.</note> as appears plainely by the woman of <hi>Samariaes</hi> diſcourſe concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Meſſias,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.25.</note> and the entertainement ſhe gaue to Chriſt: as alſo by that <hi>Samaritan</hi> leper,<note place="margin">Luc. 17.18.</note> who often that were cleanſed, was the onely man that glorified God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15174:6"/> and returned to giue thankes to his and our Sauiour.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Now when the Apoſtles, after the deſcending of the holy Ghoſt vpon them, had ſtayed ſo long in Ieruſalem, and had preached the Goſpel ſo long vnto the Iewes, as our Sauiour had appointed them, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the Martyrdome of that Proto-martyr S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Stephen,</hi> (whoſe death God turned to a bleſſed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, euen to the diſperſion of the Apoſtles, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into all other Nations) they firſt ſent <hi>Philip</hi> one of the ſeauen Deacons (as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes) to preach to the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.1. Cypr. Epiſt. 73 ad Iubaian.</note> and to baptiſe them, before the Apoſtles thought it lawfull to preach to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,<note place="margin">Act. 11.1.</note> as may be ſeene <hi>Act.</hi> 11. And no ſooner had <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> performed his office, but S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after to <hi>confirme</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Thus we finde <hi>Confirmation</hi> to bee of a <hi>more ancient</hi> ſtanding, <hi>then preaching to the Gentiles:</hi> and to haue ſet footing in the Church of Chriſt, if not <hi>with,</hi> yet <hi>preſently after</hi> the Sacrament of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 In the ſecond chapter of this Book we reade the firſt practiſe of Chriſtian Baptiſme, after Chriſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion;<note place="margin">Tertul. de Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itia c. 11.</note> for (as <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſaies) <hi>Petrus primus in Chriſti baptiſmo reſerauit aditum coeleſtis regni,</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> was the firſt of the Apoſtles, that by Baptiſme made entrance, and opened (as it were) the paſſage to the kingdom of heauen: for there in that chapter, preſently after that notable Sermon of his, diuers were baptized by him, &amp; put in hope of receiuing the holy Ghoſt &amp; his gifts, as the Apoſtles had <hi>receiued them</hi> on the day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15174:6"/> Be you baptiſed (ſaith S. <hi>Peter</hi>) in the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and <hi>yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.38</note>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 Theſe laſt words are not to bee vnderſtood of the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which are beſtowed in Baptiſme, though they follow <hi>after remiſsion of ſinnes, the propper effect of Baptiſme,</hi> as <hi>Caluin</hi> teacheth Who in that place (vpon theſe words, <hi>Et accipie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis donum Spiritus ſancti,</hi> and you ſhall receiue the gift of the Holy Ghoſt) tells vs,<note place="margin">Caluin. in Act. Apoſt. 2.38.</note> that becauſe the auditors of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> were touched with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they ſaw the Apoſtles ſpeake ſodainely with other tongues, <hi>Petrus eiuſdem doni ipſos fore compotes dicit, ſi ad Chriſtum tranſierint,</hi> Saint Peter ſayth, that they alſo ſhall become partakers of the ſame gifts of the Spirit, if they will turne to Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſtians: The chiefe gifts indeede (ſayth <hi>Caluin</hi>) were remiſſion of ſinnes, and newneſſe of life (which belong to Baptiſme there mentioned) but that promiſe, <hi>Et accipietis donum Spiritus ſancti,</hi> &amp; you ſhall <hi>receiue the Holy Ghoſt, erat velut acceſsio, vt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus alìquo dono viſibili ſuam in illis virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exercret,</hi> it was (as it were) an addition to the grace in Baptiſme, that ſo Chriſt might manifeſt his power in them by ſome viſible ſigne.</p>
            <p n="17">17 So then (as <hi>Caluin</hi> concludeth) this place is not to bee vnderſtood of the grace of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which is generally giuen to all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Baptiſme; but of another <hi>gift of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> whereof a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> or token was then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15174:7"/> giuen in the diuerſitie of tongues. <hi>Ideo hoc proprie ad nos ſpectat,</hi> therefore doth this promiſe <hi>properly</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to vs, ſaith <hi>Caluin.</hi> For though the Holy Ghoſt is not beſtowed vpon vs, that we may ſpeake with tongs, that we may propheſie, that we may cure the ſicke, and worke miracles:<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> yet is hee giuen vs for a better end, that with the heart wee may beleeue to iuſtification, that our tongues may make a good confeſſion, that we may paſſe from death to life; that we may ſtand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible againſt the world and the diuell. Thus farre <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon thoſe words, wherein Saint <hi>Peter</hi> makes promiſe of a farther gift of the Holy Ghoſt to all thoſe, that would bee baptiſed, as a meanes to draw them to be baptiſed; and here we ſee the actuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that promiſe, for the baptiſed <hi>Samaritans receiued</hi> (ſayth my text) <hi>the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and that by the miniſtery of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> who were ſent from Ieruſalem to Samaria (which was neare about thirty miles) that they might pray for the baptiſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> and <hi>lay their hands</hi> vpon them, that ſo they might receiue the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Neither was this done at that time onely, and there an end of it; but the ſame order which was here taken by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Act. 19.5. &amp; 6.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 19. Firſt he baptiſed the <hi>Epheſians, ver.</hi> 5. and then he <hi>confirmed</hi> them, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>Hee layd his hands vpon them, and the Holy Ghoſt came downe vpon them.</hi> From their example the Church learned this practiſe, and hath continued it to theſe dayes, as may be ſeene by the whole courſe of Eccleſiaſticall writers.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15174:7"/>
               <note place="margin">Bucolceri Chronol.</note>19 Saint <hi>Clement</hi> (Biſhop of Rome the ninetie fourth yeare after Chriſt) in the third of thoſe Epiſtles which are vſually aſcribed vnto him (though perhaps not his,<note place="margin">Clem. Epiſt. 3. Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liano Epiſcop:</note> yet very ancient) wiſheth euery man <hi>ſine mora renaſci Deo, &amp; demum conſignari ab Epiſcopo</hi> to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed out of hand, and then to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>confirmed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop:</hi> and he giues his reaſons for it. Becauſe (ſayth he) we are vncertaine of life; and addeth,<note place="margin">This phraſe is explained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 28.29. &amp; 89.</note> that vnleſſe each of vs bee <hi>Confirmed by the Biſhop</hi>) with the ſeuen-fold grace of the holy Spirit, <hi>perfectus eſſe Chriſtianus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaquampoterit,</hi> he cannot become a perfect Chriſtian. This was the opinion and phraſe of that author, who paſſeth vnder the name of <hi>Clement:</hi> but the phraſe you ſhall haue explained hereafter.<note place="margin">Tertull, de Baptiſmo. cap: 3:</note>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſhowes the continuance of it in his time, <hi>Egreſsi delauacro, etc.</hi> (ſayth he) When we haue aſcended out of the bath of regeneration, that is, when we haue beene baptiſed, and thoſe Ceremonies performed, which are vſed in baptiſme, <hi>Dehinc</hi> ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, <hi>manus imponitur, per benedictionem aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, et inuitans ſpiritum ſanctum,</hi> hands, holy hands, (as hee calleth them in the ſame place) are layed vpon vs, calling and inuiting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, by bleſſing vs to come downe vpon vs.</p>
            <p n="21">21 In Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> age this cuſtome of <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was continued in the Catholicke Church. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> (ſayth hee) were baptiſed by Saint <hi>Philip:</hi> therfore were they not to be rebaptiſed, hauig receiu'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15174:8"/> full, lawfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Eccleſiaſticall Baptiſme: but <hi>quod deſuerat,</hi> that <hi>which wanted,</hi> was performed by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. 73. as Iubaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. The meaning of this phraſe <hi>Quod defuerat</hi> is manifeſted, § 29.</note> And what was that? <hi>Vtoratione pro eis habita, &amp; manu impoſita, inuocaretur, &amp; infunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur ſuper eos ſpiritus ſanctus:</hi> that by prayer and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands</hi> the holy ſpirit might bee inuoked for for them, and infuſed into them. It ſeemes then, that <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> was required after Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Neither was this a <hi>prerogatiue</hi> peculiar to the <hi>Apoſtles onely,</hi> or <hi>proper to their times:</hi> no, (ſayth that worthy Father) <hi>Nunc quoque apud nos geritur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> you may ſee the ſame practiſe obſerued amongſt vs: they that are baptiſed in the Church, are brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Vt per Praepoſitos Eccleſie offerantur,</hi> that they may be offered, or preſented to God by the <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the Church</hi> (he meanes the Biſhops, whereof he was one) <hi>et per noſtram orationem, ac manus impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem ſpiritum ſanctum conſequantur,</hi> that by our prayer, and <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> they may receiue the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>&amp; ſignaculo dominico conſummentur,</hi> and be made perfit by the <hi>Lords ſigne;</hi> for ſo they called the <hi>ſigne of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 Here you may ſee all the circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that I deriued from this my text; number them, and you ſhall finde them here. Firſt the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> were <hi>confirmed by Saint Peter and Saint Iohn,</hi> ſaith Saint Cyprian: there is the <hi>Antiquitie of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> in his judgement. Secondly. The <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Confirmation in his time were <hi>Praepoſiti Eccleſiae,</hi> the Gouernors or Biſhops of the Church. Thirdly: The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15174:8"/> 
               <hi>perſons</hi> capable of Confirmation, <hi>qui in Eccleſia bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantur,</hi> ſuch as are <hi>baptiſed</hi> in the Church of Chriſt. Fourthly: The <hi>forme</hi> of Confirmation vſed in Saint Cyprians age, was <hi>oratto, ac manus Impoſitio, prayer and impoſition of hands.</hi> Fifthly, By prayer, and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands <hi>Spiritum ſanctum conſequuntur,</hi> they receiue the Holy Ghoſt, there is the <hi>effect.</hi> And here is one Ceremony more added (as it ſeemes) by the Church, before Saint Cyprians time, namely, <hi>to conclude Confirmation with the ſigne of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 A ſigne ſo generally receiued in Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> time, that hee makes it a wonder, if any man ſhould be ignorant of it. <hi>Quid eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 118 in Io, Euan.</note> 
               <hi>quod omnes nouerunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti, niſi crux Chriſti?</hi> What is that, which all the world takes notice of? That ſigne of Chriſt, what is it but the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of Chriſt? And ſo highly was it eſteemed by him, and the holy men of that age,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that he profeſſeth, vnleſſe it be added <hi>ſiue frontibus creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſiue ipſi aquae, quare generantur; ſiue olco, quo Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate vnguntur:</hi> vnleſſe (ſayth hee) the ſigne of the Croſſe be vſed in Baptiſme and in Confirmation: <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil eorum rite perficitur,</hi> none of them are rightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: that is, according to the orders and rites of the Church.</p>
            <p n="25">25 So Saint Auſtine. The Croſſe therefore, vpon this or the like conſideration, is enioyned to be vſed in Confirmation, in the booke of Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſet forth, and allowed in Edward the ſixts raigne: and I finde it not at any time reuoked; but it is left (as it ſeemes) to the Biſhops diſcretion to vſe, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15174:9"/> not vſe the Croſſe in Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Neither doe we deduce the antiquitie of this ceremonie of the Croſſe, from S. <hi>Auſtins,</hi> or S. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> age onely; but we goe higher to the times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Tertul.</hi> and <hi>Clemen. Alexand.</hi> flouriſhed: <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaies,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. carnis.</note> 
               <hi>Caro ſignatur, Vt &amp; anima muniatur;</hi> the body is ſigned with the Croſſe (in confirmation,) that the ſoule may bee fenced againſt all temptations: and <hi>Clem. Alexand.</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> notes) obſerues not onely the practiſe of <hi>Confirmation in S. Iohn time,</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all this Ceremonie of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> whereby this <hi>Signe</hi> ſeemes alſo to be <hi>Apoſtolike:</hi> for S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle hauing newly conſtituted a Biſhop in Aſia,<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ. l. 3. c. 20.</note> deliuered him a goodly proper young man, (whom hee had a great liking to) to be trained vp by him in Chriſtian religion. The Biſhop tooke him, and brought him vp with great care and diligence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and at laſt hee enlightened him; that is, baptiſed him.<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Eccleſ. literar. c. 2.</note> For the ancient Fathers, and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> call Baptiſme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> illumination, becauſe in Baptiſme a man is enlightned in the faith of Chriſt. And this phraſe they ſeeme to borrow from Saint <hi>Paul, Hebr.</hi> 6 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. It is impoſſible, that they,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.</note> who haue once beene <hi>enlightened,</hi> that is bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zed,<note place="margin">Ver. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Rurſus renouari ad poenitentiam,</hi> ſhould be renewed vnto repentance; that is, (as S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſayth) ſhould bee baptized againe with that Sacrament of repentance. <hi>Aug. de vera &amp; falſa poenitentia. c.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15174:9"/>27. Well, the Biſhop hauing thus baptiſed this young man, committed and commended to his charge, he had ſuch are ouer him, he gaue him ſo good, and ſo Chriſtian education, that at laſt he added <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ. l. 3. c. 20.</note> the Seale of the Lord, meaning Confirmation (which was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the ſigne of the croſſe) which was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as a <hi>defence,</hi> or <hi>ſafegard</hi> from thoſe powerful enemies ſinne and the Deuill, (ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vſeth the word) or as an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt poyſon, (ſo Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans call it:) and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laſt,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Eccleſ. hierar. c. 3.</note> the <hi>moſt perfect defence,</hi> he could adde vnto him; which was <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Not as though children being baptiſed were not fully Chriſtians, not ſo:<note place="margin">Common prayer. booke</note> for (as our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer booke</hi> ſaves well) <hi>Children being baptiſed, haue all things neceſſarie for their ſaluation, and be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſaued;</hi> yet ſhall wee finde a different <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Confirmation,</hi> from that <hi>perfection,</hi> which we receiue <hi>in Baptiſme. Baptiſmus perficit in ſuo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> true it is, <hi>that Baptiſme perfits</hi> in his owne kind, but <hi>Confirmation</hi> in another kinde. Will you ſee the difference? The holy Ghoſt at the font <hi>pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem tribuit ad innocentium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho 3. q. 72. 1. c ex Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiade. P. can. 2. de conſecr. diſt. 5.</note> giues vs <hi>innocencie</hi> at full, but in Confirmation <hi>Augmentum praeſtat ad gratiam,</hi> he grants vs an increaſe <hi>in grace:</hi> in Baptiſme <hi>regeneramur ad vitam,</hi> wee are <hi>regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15174:10"/> to life, but by <hi>Impoſition of hands, Confirmamur ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnam,</hi> wee are <hi>ſtrengthned</hi> to fight the Lords bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes. So then theſe things, which are of the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of a Chriſtian are not giuen in <hi>Confirmation,</hi> but in <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> for in Baptiſme we receiue thoſe things, <hi>quae ſunt de planitudine ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae,</hi> which are of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſufficiencie, which are fully ſufficient to bring vs to ſaluation: but in <hi>Confirmation</hi> thoſe things are added to vs, <hi>quae ſunt de plenitudine abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantiae,</hi> which are of the fulneſſe of abundance,<note place="margin">Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rez in 3. Tho. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 12. Diſp. 38. Sect. 1.</note> which make our paſſage to heauen the more eaſie: and theſe ought not to bee accounted <hi>ſimpliciter neceſſaria,</hi> (ſay the ſchooles) ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply neceſſary to ſaluation. And for this cauſe (it ſeemes) <hi>Clem.</hi> ſayth, that hee, who careleſſely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully omits <hi>Confirmation,</hi> cannot become a perfect <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> and yet he denyes not but a <hi>man may be a true and iuſt Chriſtian without Confirmation:</hi> both which hee is by Baptiſme. For <hi>in Baptiſme</hi> we receiue <hi>perfect iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication:</hi> but <hi>in Confirmation our ſanctification is in ſome good meaſure augmented,</hi> and is dayly increaſed in vs more and more by the bleſſed Euchariſt, and other religious actions.</p>
            <p n="29">29 Will you accept of a Simile? An infant newly borne is a man, <hi>a perfit man quoad eſſentiam,</hi> according to eſſence, but he is <hi>not perfit quoad molem</hi> in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie and ſtature: neither can an infant performe thoſe actions, which are required of man, vnleſſe age and ſtrength make the addition. I will leaue the aplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your ſelues, and tell you Tertullians opinion. He ſayth, that in Baptiſme we receiue <hi>illum Dei ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15174:10"/> that ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">Tertul. ad. Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. o. ca. 5.</note> which Adam receiued from God in his creation, and loſt afterwards by his fall. So then <hi>Innocencie</hi> wee receiue by <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> but with Adam we want <hi>the ſpirit of Confirmation,</hi> and therefore are we eaſie to bee ſeduced, as hee was. Wherefore a ſupply is to be made: <hi>dehinc</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>manus imponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſhortly after followes <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid e 8.</note> that thereby receiuing ſtrength wee may be the better able to withſtand the aſſaults of the world, the fleſh, and the deuill: and this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that perfection, which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <hi>by</hi> and <hi>in</hi> Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Neither was this onely a matter of <hi>practiſe</hi> in in the Apoſtles times, but it was an eſpeciall poynt of <hi>doctrine</hi> alſo; wherein the <hi>Neophyti</hi> new-borne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were primarily informed euen by the Apoſtles themſelues. For there were in thoſe dayes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome <hi>new-borne babes,</hi> and ſome of perfect age,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2. 1. Cor. 2.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>perfecti;</hi> and as there was milke for yong Catechiſts, ſo was there alſo ſtrong meate for the elder profeſſors of religion. <hi>Sapientiam loquimur inter perfectos:</hi> it was a rule Saint Paul himſelfe obſerued, to ſpeake of high myſteries onely <hi>to</hi> and <hi>amongſt</hi> thoſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.6.</note> who are well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Chriſtianitie.</p>
            <p n="31">31 So then, that euery one might be informed in that doctrine, which was fitting for him, there was in the Apoſtles times <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt, or (as we now reade) The principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, that is, a <hi>Catechiſme for</hi> thoſe <hi>little ones,</hi> which contained a briefe ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie of thoſe principles which were neceſſary for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15174:11"/> Chriſtian to learne. Amongſt theſe principles <hi>Confirmation</hi> was one,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> as is to be ſeene. <hi>Heb</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="32">32 Therefore ſaying aſide (ſaith the Apoſtle) the principles of religion or Chriſtianitie, <hi>ad perfectionem feramur,</hi> let vs goe forward to perfection: let vs leaue <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.</note> and haſte to matters of a deeper reach, we will entreats of high myſteries, of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and his Prieſthood, and how he was a type of Chriſt. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="33">33 Now theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this Catechiſme, theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> which the Apoſtle for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent would ſay aſide, are thus reckoned by him. Firſt, <hi>Repentance</hi> from dead workes. Secondly,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> towards God. Thirdly, The doctrine of <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi> that is, <hi>Confirmation.</hi> Fifthly, The article of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> from the dead. And laſtly, the certaintie of <hi>Eternall Iudgement.</hi> Theſe were the chiefe, the maine points of the <hi>Apoſtles Catechiſme,</hi> and in theſe chiefly were the yonger ſort of thoſe times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed:<note place="margin">Engliſh marg. notes.</note> and therefore the Engliſh marginall notes fitly tearme them the <hi>firſt principles,</hi> the <hi>firſt rudiments of Chriſtian religion,</hi> the <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> that was then in vſe. Whereby we gather, that all theſe are <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal points of religion,</hi> euery one of them. And (it ſeems) they were ſo generally, ſo faithfully receiued, beleeued, and practiſed at that time, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had no need to incite them to the embracing of theſe articles.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <note place="margin">Heb 6.2. Caluin. Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. cap: 6.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>34 And that you may not doubt, that <hi>Confirmation</hi> is <hi>meant by impoſition of hands</hi> in this place, <hi>Caluin</hi> plainely tells vs, that <hi>Vnus hic locus abunde teſtatur, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15174:11"/> Ceremoniae originem fluxiſſe ab Apoſtolis.</hi> This one onely place doth fully teſtifie, that this Ceremonie (of <hi>Confirmation</hi>) tooke his beginning from the Apoſtles themſelues; which Ceremonie (ſaith he) was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed, for they fained it to be a Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="35">35 Theſe Articles mentioned Heb. 6. or ſome ſuch like,<note place="margin">Heb. 6 2.</note> were (no doubt) that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that manner of Catechiſing, <hi>In quam</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans) traditi eſtis,</hi> whereunto you were deliuered, or (as we reade) which was deliuered to you.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note> It is not (I confeſſe) ſo proper a phraſe in Engliſh, or Latin to ſay, <hi>To this forme of doctrine or Catechiſing, you were deliuered,</hi> as, <hi>This forme of doctrine was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to you:</hi> but yet the Apoſtle expreſſeth it ſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in quam traditi eſtis:</hi> and <hi>Catetan</hi> obſerues well, that the Apoſtle changed the ordinary phraſe <hi>ratione myſterij,</hi> becauſe of the myſterie; for hereby (ſaith he) is ſignified,<note place="margin">Caiet. in Rom. 6:</note> 
               <hi>quod non tam Euangelicae doctrinae forma tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita èſt hominibus, quàm quòd homines traditi ſunt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae doctrinae Euangelicae;</hi> that, not ſo much the forme of religion was deliuered to men, as that men were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the forme of religion; that ſo by this meanes religion might be knowen to haue authority and power ouer man, but not man ouer religion.</p>
            <p n="36">36 Now, that Confirmation was reckoned <hi>inter initia fidei</hi> amongſt the rudiments, &amp; grounds of faith in the Apoſtles times, and ſo held, and practiſed in the next ſucceeding ages, we neede not ſeeke farre for proofe: the <hi>practiſe</hi> may be gathered from my Text;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15174:12"/> the <hi>doctrine,</hi> whereon we may ſettle our faith, is cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught in that <hi>Catechiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. which (it ſeemes) was very early on foot, and in vſe amongſt Chriſtians. There in the Apoſtles <hi>Catechiſme</hi> it is called <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum impoſitionis manuum,</hi> (and he knew what he ſpoke) <hi>the foundation of Impoſition of hands,</hi> as being a <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall point of religion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> The phraſe of the holy Spirit is well worth the marking, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Impoſition of hands. He then that takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Confirmation,</hi> ſhakes a <hi>foundation of religion,</hi> he remoues one of the ground-ſtones of our ſaith.</p>
            <p n="37">37 In S. <hi>Pauls</hi> iudgement then it is <hi>a fundamentall point of faith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Engliſh marg. notes.</note> and as the marginall notes ſay, <hi>one of the firſt rudiments of our religion:</hi> and it might well bee deliuered in that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom.6.17.</note> For <hi>Tertul.</hi> relating the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (which in his time was <hi>ſtatu foelix Eccleſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 36</note> as he cals it, an happie, and bleſſed Church) tels vs, how ſhe beleeued in God the Father, God the Sonne, &amp;c: and then hee addes, <hi>Aquae ſignat, Sancto Spiritu veſtit, Euchariſtia paſcit,</hi> ſhe ſignes with water <hi>(in Baptiſme,)</hi> clothes with the holy Spirit <hi>(in Confirmation,)</hi> feeds with the bleſſed Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt <hi>(in the Communion,)</hi> and then thoſe that are thus armed, thus well prouided, <hi>martyrio exhortatur,</hi> ſhee exhorts to Martyrdome, <hi>&amp; aduerſus hanc inſtitutionem neminem recipit,</hi> ſhe receiues no man into the Church without theſe conditions.</p>
            <p n="38">38 Neither was this the doctrine of the Church of Rome onely, but it was common to her with other Churches,<note place="margin">Tertul. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Cum Aphricanis quoque Eccleſijs</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15174:12"/> hanc, fidem conteſſarauit,</hi> all the Churches of Affricke ioyned with her in this faith, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affricke, but alſo Achaia, Macedonia, and Aſia.</p>
            <p n="39">39 For we may well ſuppoſe, that in the Apoſtles times, and practiſe, <hi>whereſoeuer Baptiſme went before, Confirmation followed after,</hi> and where mention is made of the conuerſion of the Iewes, or Gentiles, and their faith in Chriſt Ieſus the ſonne of God, there the whole <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the forme of doctrine, the Apoſtles Creede, and their Catechiſme (we ſpoke of) were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and entertained alſo. For the Eunuch whom S. <hi>Philip</hi> baptiſed, ſayd no more (for ought we reade) but this, <hi>I beleeue, that Chriſt Ieſus is the ſonne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.37.</note> and in that profeſſion was preſently baptiſed. <hi>Num ergo placet</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine) vt hoc ſolum homines reſpondeant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Fide &amp; Operibus. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; continuo baptizentur?</hi> Doth this therefore content, &amp; pleaſe you? Thinke you this ſufficient, that men ſhould make this anſwer onely, and be preſently baptiſed, and yet confeſſe nothing of the Catholicke Church, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of remiſſion of ſinnes, and thoſe ſeuerall articles, which are named in the Apoſtles Creed? Well, if this Eunuchs briefe anſwer were ſufficient to procure preſent Baptiſme, and licence to depart: why doe not wee take the ſame courſe (ſayth Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>) and in caſe of neceſſitie, <hi>cum ad baptizandum vrget tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris auguſtia,</hi> when the ſtraitneſſe of time vrgeth vs to baptiſe, why doe not wee take away thoſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and interrogations, which we hold neceſſary to expreſſe at the time of baptiſme? Why certainly (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine) ſi Scriptura tacuit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>atque intelligenda ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15174:13"/> caetera,</hi> if the Scripture paſſed if ouer the reſt in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and left them to be vnderſtood; then ſurely, when the Scripture tells, that Saint <hi>Philip</hi> baptiſed the Eunucu, <hi>in co intelligi voluit impleta omnia,</hi> in that one word it would haue you vnderſtand, that all things were performed, which are requiſite to Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="40">40 In like manner, when we reade, that the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers were baptiſed in euery countrey, where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles came, we muſt thinke, that <hi>confirmation</hi> followed after,<note place="margin">Aug. Ib.</note> and the holy Euchariſt, &amp;c. <hi>quae licet taceantur in Scripturis gratia breuitatis tamen ſerie traditionis ſcimus implenda,</hi> which though they be omitted in Scripture for breuitie ſake, yet we know by the continuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Church of Rome, Affricke, Achaia, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,<note place="margin">Tertull. de praeſer. c. 36.</note> and Aſia, (as <hi>Tertullian notes</hi>) that they were to be performed. <hi>Hoc eſt enim Euangelizare Chriſtum non tantum dicere (aut docere) quae ſunt credenda de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augale Fide &amp; operibus. c. 9,</note> 
               <hi>ſed etiam quae obſeruanda ei, qui accedit ad compagem corporis Chriſti:</hi> this is to preach Chriſt aright, not onely to confeſſe or teach thoſe things, which are to be beleeued concerning Chriſt, but thoſe alſo, which muſt be obſerued, and performed by euery man, that is to be ingrafted into the body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="41">41 Thus you ſee, that whereſoeuer Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> came, and conſequently the reſt of the Apoſtles, there the doctrine of Confirmation paſſed for currant. And (which is worth the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in all the Fathers writings <hi>Confirmation</hi> takes his place <hi>next to Baptiſme,</hi> as being euer to ſucceede Baptiſme. This courſe the Apoſtles beganne, and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15174:13"/> Fathers followed their ſteps, as you haue heard out of <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> who euer giue <hi>confirmation</hi> the <hi>next place to Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="42">42 This were ſufficient to proue the Antiquitie of this Ceremonie, or Myſtery, if we were fully perſwaded that this were the true and natiue ſenſe of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which haue beene cited. But ſome, who in their church-gouernment admit no Hierarchie, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently deny the order of Biſhops, muſt not admit of confirmation, nor of thoſe receiued interpretations of Scripture, which make for <hi>confirmation. Quibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſuit propoſitum al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er docendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull de praeſer. c. 38.</note> 
               <hi>eos neceſsitas coegita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter diſponendi inſtrumenta doctrinae:</hi> they that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued not to admit of Biſhops, were of neceſſitie to interpret thoſe places otherwiſe, which make for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>ſeruice performable by Biſhops onely:</hi> and therefore theſe new Doctors labor and ſtriue to elude the teſtimonies &amp; practiſes of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtles, by falſe and friuoulous expoſitions, ſuch as were neuer heard of till theſe latter times.<note place="margin">Tertull. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Sed illic et Scripturarum, et expoſitionum adulteratio deputan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt, vbi diuerſitas inuenitur doctrinae:</hi> but for certaine there is the adulterating both of Scripture, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Scripture, where there is a diuers doctrine from the Apoſtles, and the primitiue times.</p>
            <p n="43">43 Behold here a late doctrine, a ſtrange expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of holy writ. Theſe expoſitors tell vs, that this <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> was <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and giuen onely to the Apoſtles, as a gift proper, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiars to thoſe times; not for the encreaſe of grace, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15174:14"/> ſtrength of faith, no; but for the gift of tongues, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſiying, and ſuch like ſtrange miracles, which were then requiſit for the propagation of the Goſpel in the beginning, but ſoone after ceaſed, and ſo the <hi>effect of Impoſition of hands</hi> (it ſeems by them) was onely <hi>gratia gratis data,</hi> and not <hi>gratia gratum faciens,</hi> a glorious, not a gracious gift. For if theſe two gifts be well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the former will appeare to be chiefly giuen for the good of others, <hi>in gloriam gratiae,</hi> to ſet forth the glory of that grace, which came by Chriſt into the world: &amp; he that hath this gift may be a tinckling Cymball, and no more: but the latter,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> that ſame <hi>gratia gratum faciens,</hi> that excellent gift is infuſed into vs for our own good <hi>in gratiam gloriae,</hi> that ſo being partakers of grace in this life, we may be heyres of glory in the life to come: for by this grace the Spirit beareth witneſſe with out ſpirit,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.6.</note> that we are the ſonnes of God.</p>
            <p n="44">44 But this euaſion is repugnant to the true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſence of holy Scripture: for that of Chriſt to his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Luc. 24.49.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>Sedete in ciuitate, donec induamini virtute ex alto, Tarry in the citie of Ieruſalem, vntill ye be indued with power from aboue,</hi>) did not onely, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoſe externall and glorious gifts of miracles, tongs propheſiyng, and the like, which they had <hi>ad incremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Euangelti,</hi> for the increaſe of the Goſpell; but other internall &amp; comfortable graces alſo of the holy Ghoſt which they had infuſed into them, <hi>ad incrementum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei, &amp; ſanctitatis,</hi> for their owne peculiar ſanctification. Otherwiſe thoſe externall gifts might haue bene but fallacious, fruitleſſe ſymboles, glorious ſhowes, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15174:14"/> ſhadowes, and (the truth is) had little, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing avayled themſelues.</p>
            <p n="45">45 But if we looke well into the text, we ſhall find there, that on the day of Pentecoſt, when the Apoſtles receiued thoſe goodly miraculous gifts, <hi>ſimulindueban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur virtute ex alto,</hi> they were alſo endued with power from aboue, not onely that they might ſpeake with tongs, <hi>ſed vt loquerentur linguis magnalia Dei,</hi> but that they might ſpeake the wonderfull workes of God:<note place="margin">Act. 2 11.</note> nor that only, to edifie others, &amp; to be as bels to tole others to Church, and be nere the better themſelues: but ſo to confirme, and ſtrengthen them in their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, <hi>vt cum fiducia loquerentur verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 4.31. &amp;, 33.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute magna redderent teſtimonium reſurrectionis Chriſti,</hi> that they might ſpeake the word of God boldly, and with great power beare witnes of the reſurrection of Chriſt. Before they were <hi>orphani</hi> (as our Sauior terms them) orphans, comfortleſſe, fearefull orphans:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.18. Mat. 26.70.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> denyed his maſter to ſilly mayde; but being once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimed by this Comforter, hauing receiued the holy Ghoſt, they become <hi>potentes ad praelium,</hi> mighty in the battels of the Lord, the worthies of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.9.</note> the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the world; men &amp; Angels ſtand amazed at their conſtancy and courage. So then they receiued not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outward, but inward gifts and graces alſo, by the deſcent of the holy Ghoſt vpon them.</p>
            <p n="46">46 As for thoſe external gifts of the H. Ghoſt, though they haue long ſince ceaſed, &amp; are not now conferd by <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> yet they continued in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> time,<note place="margin">Iren. 12 c 5.</note> as himſelf witneſſes; (&amp; he liued 178 years after Chriſt and we find not any where,<note place="margin">Bucol. Chron.</note> that thoſe miraculous gifts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15174:15"/> were conferred by any, ſaue <hi>onely Biſhops,</hi> the Apoſtles ſucceſſors for a time euen in that power.</p>
            <p n="47">
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat l. 3. c. 16.</note>47 But howeuer thoſe wonderfull gifts, and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous graces are now aboliſhed, yet the inward gifts of ſanctification, of fortitude, of loue, and charitie, are at this day continued in the Church, by the miniſtery of Biſhops in Confirmation. So Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="48">
               <note place="margin">Ber ſer. 1. in Pentecoſt</note>48 And a long time after him Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe two diſtinct graces of the holy Ghoſt, tells vs concerning the former, that <hi>Nobis illa manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio potius, quam Apoſtolis facta eſt,</hi> the gift of tongues, propheſing, &amp;c. was rather for our good, then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles benefit; they tooke the paynes, wee reape the profit: but there was (ſayth he) another manifeſtation of the ſpirit <hi>in cis</hi> in them, which concerned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt, <hi>et haec vſque bodiè fit in nobis,</hi> and this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at theſe dayes is wrought in vs.</p>
            <p n="49">49 Some there are, (I know) that make queſtion, whether by <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> wee receiue the holy Ghoſt, ſeeing wee receiue not thoſe externall gifts of the holy Ghoſt. But Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> takes vp ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioniſts very roundly.<note place="margin">Aug. tract 6. in Epiſt. Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>Numquid</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>quia mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula non edunt,</hi> what, becauſe they worke no miracles, becauſe they ſpeak not with tongs, becauſe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie not, <hi>ita peruerſo corde aliquis veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuit,</hi> is any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt you of ſo peruerſe a diſpoſition, ſo froward a ſpirit, ſo incredulous, that he dare affirme, that theſe <hi>confirmed chriſtians</hi> haue not receiu'd the holy Ghoſt? Wilt thou know certainely, whether thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Ghoſt or no?<note place="margin">Aug. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Interroga cor tuum</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15174:15"/> that worthy Father) look into thy heart, aske thy ſoule and conſcience, and that will tell thee, if perchance thou haſt receiued <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and not the benefit of Confirmation: for it is in this holy rite, as in the bleſſed Euchariſt, <hi>Recipitur ad modum recipientis,</hi> it is receiued, as the receiuer is diſpoſed, whether well or ill. Receiue it therefore cheerefully, reuerently, and thankfully, and without all doubt, you ſhall be endued with power fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, which ſhal helpe you forward in the way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p n="50">50 This S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> makes euident againſt the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts; for he ſhews the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that there are <hi>three things to bee obſerued in confirmation.</hi> One is the Sacrament it ſelfe;<note place="margin">Aug de Bapt. cont. Donat. l. 3. c. 16. Aug de Doct. Chriſt. l. 3. c. 9. Aug. Epiſt. 118 ad lanuar. Hook, Eccl. po. l. 5. §. 66</note> as he cals it (<hi>a Sacrament not of that excellencie,</hi> as to bee ranked with the bleſſed Euchariſt, &amp; Baptiſme, as is to be ſeene in his 3. booke <hi>de doct. Chriſt.</hi> &amp; in his 118. Ep. but as M. <hi>Hooker</hi> termes it, <hi>a Sacramentall complement</hi>) which <hi>Sacramentall complement</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine) etiam Simon Magus habere potuit, Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus</hi> might haue had for he was baptiſed. The 2. is <hi>operatio quaedam ſpiritus</hi> a certaine kinde of operation of the, ſame Spirite, wrought by <hi>impoſition of hands, quae in malis hominibus etiam fieri ſolet,</hi> which was vſuall euen in bad men; as the gift of propheſie,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 10.</note> which king <hi>Saul</hi> had euen at that time, when he perſecuted <hi>Dauid:</hi> and thoſe gifts of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, which <hi>Simon Magus</hi> wold haue bought for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,<note place="margin">Act. 8.18.</note> and are now ceaſed. The third is <hi>operatio eiuſdem ſpiritus,</hi> the high operation, euen the gifts and graces of the ſame ſpirit, to ſtrengthen &amp; confirm Chriſtians in the true faith; to maintaine and increaſe loue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15174:16"/> and charitie amongſt profeſſed, and beleeuing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p n="51">51 Of the <hi>firſt</hi> all Chriſtians are capable, that is, of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> both then, and euer ſince: of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, viz. the <hi>operatione of miracles,</hi> all were capable, both good and bad in thoſe dayes,<note place="margin">Aug de Bap con. Dona l. 3. c. 16.</note> as it pleaſed the ſpirit to diſpoſe thoſe gifts: of the third, that is, the <hi>good and bleſſed worke</hi> of vnitie and charitie, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, neither hereticke nor ſchiſmaticke is capable; but onely thoſe, who liue quietly &amp; peaceably in the Catholicke Church.</p>
            <p n="52">52. Hereby it appeares <hi>firſt;</hi> that <hi>not onely</hi> thoſe <hi>externall gifts</hi> of miracles, tongues, &amp;c. were giuen by <hi>Impoſition of hands:</hi> but the <hi>externall graces</hi> alſo of the holy Ghoſt, who promiſed to continue with the Church to the end of the world.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.</note> For when our bleſſed Sauior made that promiſe of <hi>ſending the holy Spirite,</hi> he not onely ſayd, I will pray the Father, and he ſhal ſend you another a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forter:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.1.17 10</note> but he makes the ſame prayer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for his Apoſtles &amp; Diſciples, who were then preſent, and generally for all thoſe, that ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in his name through the Apoſtles, and Diſciples preaching. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> prophetically (before he knew it belonged vnto the Gentiles) expounds this promiſe to be made to you (Iewes) &amp; to your children, and to al that are a farre off, euen as many, as the Lord our God ſhould call. And this could not poſſibly hold true, if it were onely ſpoke of theſe <hi>glorious gifts,</hi> which are manifeſt to the outward eye, and are now ceaſed.</p>
            <p n="53">53. Secondly, That this promiſe of the holy Ghoſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15174:16"/> made by our Sauiour, aimed not meerely <hi>ad gratias gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis datas,</hi> at the externall miraculous gifts; but chiefly <hi>ad gratiam ſanctificantem</hi> at that inviſible ſanctifying grace, witneſſe our Sauiour himſelfe, <hi>Expedit vobis, vt ego vadam,</hi> Iohn 16. It is expedient for you, that I leaue you; for if I depart not from you,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.17.</note> that <hi>Comforter</hi> will not come vnto you; but if I goe, then will I ſend him to you. Now if the holy Ghoſt were not giuen <hi>ad corroborandum, et ſanctificandum,</hi> to confirme their faith, and ſanctifie their conuerſation, then might theſe gifts ſerue rather <hi>ad inflandum,</hi> to puffe them vp by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, tongues, propheſying, &amp;c. which would ſooner breed a conceit of glory, then any encreaſe of grace; and are more for the behoofe of others, then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers benefits; as I noted before out of Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. Ser. 1. in Pentecoſt.</note> And then were not thoſe gifts of ſo great worth, that they ſhould be preferd before the corporall preſence of our bleſſed Sauiour; vnleſſe it were by <hi>Simon Magus</hi> or ſome ſuch vaine-glorious hypocrite.</p>
            <p n="54">54 Thirdly, thoſe miraculous gifts of the holy Ghoſt were not common alike to all beleeuers, but the Spirit diſtributed them at his pleaſure, as he thought beſt, <hi>ad dilatanda Eccleſiae primordia,</hi> for the good of the Church, and increaſe of Chriſtianity:<note place="margin">Aug. de Bap. cont. Donat. l. 3. c. 16.</note> but this gift (wee now treat of) was giuen to all the faithfull by <hi>Impoſition of the Apoſtles hands:</hi> for the <hi>Apoſtles layed their hands</hi> vpon thoſe that were baptiſed.<note place="margin">Act 8 17. Act 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>Actes</hi> 8. &amp; <hi>Actes</hi> 19. both Samaritans, and Epheſians, and all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the holy Ghoſt; yet all wrought not miracles: So S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Are al Apoſtles? are all Prophets?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.29.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15174:17"/> are all teachers? are al workers of miracles? Haue al the gifts of healing?<note place="margin">Lyra in locum 4.</note> do all ſpeake with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongs? do all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret? As if he ſhould ſay, no, they do not. So <hi>Lyra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="55">55. Fourthly, when the Apoſtle reckons <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> amongſt the <hi>principles</hi> of Chriſtian religion,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> and thoſe <hi>fundamentall points</hi> of faith, wherein the yonger ſort was, and is to be trained vp, it cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be imagined, that it belongs onely to thoſe viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and miraculous ſignes (for then were it no <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall point</hi> of religion, and to what end ſhould chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be inſtructed in it?) but it belongs rather (as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> notes) <hi>ad confirmationem vnitatis in Eccleſia Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Heb. 6.</note> to the <hi>confirming</hi> of vnitie in the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeſt 44. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Non. Teſt.</note> and this (ſaith he) <hi>poſt baptiſmum à Pontificibus fieri ſolet,</hi> was vſually done <hi>after</hi> (not <hi>afore</hi>) baptiſme, <hi>by the Biſhops;</hi> and <hi>onely by the Biſhops,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="56">56. Finally, it is a reaſon ſufficient to proue, that <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> wrought not wonders onely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what the Apoſtles did here to the Samaritans, the ſame forme of bleſſing hath euer ſince continued in the Church: and the effect, the bleſſing it ſelfe hath (I doubt not) beene deriued to vs <hi>by the Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>only by the Biſhops, the Apoſtles onely ſucceſſors in this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melch. Can. 3. de conſecr. Diſt 5. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt. 37. Dom Epiſc. Rauenna c. 2.</note> for which cauſe it was named heretofore <hi>Manus impoſitio Epiſcoporum,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopalis manuum impoſitio,</hi> as at this day it is called <hi>Biſhopping</hi> with vs, ſhewing by the very name, that our ancients held it the proper, and peculiar office of the Biſhop. <hi>Optatus</hi> therefore prouing that <hi>Macharius</hi> was no Biſhop, brings this for a maine argument,<note place="margin">Optat. Mileuit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ht. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. l. 7</note> 
               <hi>Nec in of ficio Epiſcopali verſatus eſt,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15174:17"/> nec manum alicutampoſuit,</hi> he performed not the office of a Biſhop, he vſed not impoſition of hands, and therefore he was no Biſhop.</p>
            <p n="57">57 <hi>The Apoſtles onely</hi> did it in their times, <hi>not the Diſciples, not Deacons,</hi> not <hi>Philip,</hi> no (ſayth Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome) he might not do it: neque enim facultatem habetat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ, hom. 18 in Act. Apost.</note> for he had no ſuch power, no ſuch authority, but Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> (who were <hi>Apoſtles</hi>) they might they did <hi>confirme:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſo. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc enim donum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome) ſolorum Apoſtolorum erat,</hi> this gift belonged to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles onely: and the truth is (as the ſame Father pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes) <hi>Hoc erat in Apoſtolis ſingulare,</hi> this authority was ſingular in the Apoſtles: <hi>the Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>only the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> could beſtow this gift of the holy Ghoſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;<note place="margin">Hier ad Marc-cp. 54. aduerſus Montanum. Cypr. ad Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum: Epi. 73.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; apud nos</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Ierome) Apoſtolorum locum tenem Epiſcopt,</hi> in Churches orthodoxe (ſuch as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> liued in) the <hi>Biſhops hold the Apoſtles roome:</hi> &amp; therfore S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> tels vs, that the Apoſtles did that in their daies, <hi>quod nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c geritur,</hi> which was practiſed in his time, &amp; S. <hi>Auſt.</hi> relating how the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> praied, &amp; <hi>layd their hands</hi> on the Samaritans, that the H. ghoſt might come down vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ads inſtantly,<note place="margin">Aug. de Trin. l. 15. c 26.</note> 
               <hi>Quem more in ſuis Praepoſitis etiam nunc ſeruat Eccleſia,</hi> which is the ſame with S. <hi>Cyp.</hi> naming alſo the Miniſters of this bleſſing, <hi>Praepoſitos,</hi> the Biſhops of the Church. And this is no more then <hi>Cal.</hi> acknowledges in his <hi>Inſtit. Hic mos olim fuit,</hi> this was a cuſtome long ſince (ſaith <hi>Cal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calu. Inſtit. l. 4. c. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note>) that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians children, when they come to yeares of diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould be brought before the Biſhop to be confirmed: &amp; this he cals <hi>ſolenne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> benedictione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a ſolemn benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15174:18"/> and then he brings in that of S. <hi>Iero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom. cont. Lucifer. c. 4.</note> who avowes it to be <hi>Apoſtolicam obſeruationem,</hi> and Apoſtolicke obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, or inſtitution: howeuer hee ſeemes not very well pleaſed with that Father for affirming it.</p>
            <p n="58">58 Thus you ſee, how we haue deduced the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie of Confirmation</hi> from the Apoſtles themſelues, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if from them, ſure from God: for euery ordinance Apoſtolike we take to be the action of the holy Ghoſt:<note place="margin">Caluin. Inſtit. l. 1 c 9. §. 6.</note> and by <hi>Caluins</hi> conſent, we are no way to be blamed, ſo long as we imitate an example Apoſtolicke: but they are rather to be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, who forſake this holy, and Apoſtolicke Inſtitution. <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> therefore ſpeaking of Impoſition of hands, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knwoledgeth, what we all confeſſe, that wee haue no precept for it,<note place="margin">Zanch. in 4. praecept.</note> 
               <hi>interim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>exempla Apoſtolorum, &amp; veteris Eccleſiae vellem pluris aeſtimari,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I could wiſh, that the example of the Apoſtles, and of the ancient Church might haue better eſteeme amongſt vs: <hi>immò deberent nobis eſſe inſtar legis diuinae,</hi> yea (ſaith he) their examples ſhould be to vs as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine precept.</p>
            <p n="59">59 For continuance of Confirmation in the Church (if I were ambitious in this kind) I could paſſe through the Church Hiſtorie, Councels, and Fathers to this preſent day: but much hath beene ſpoken concerning it already, and I will not cleane tire out your patience, I will only alledge two or three notable inſtances, which make much for the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="60">60 I will beginne with <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who was Biſhop
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15174:18"/> of <hi>Rome</hi> 250. yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s after Chriſt. This worthy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr writing to <hi>Fabian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> concerning <hi>Nouatus the Puritan hereticke,</hi> (for <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ. l. 6. c. 42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> notes him to be the ring-leader of all thoſe, <hi>qui mente inflati ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſos puros eſſe profitentur,</hi> who are the onely <hi>pure men</hi> in their owne conceits) reports, how he was poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a Deuil (as all heretickes are little better) and being deliuered by the exorciſts of thoſe times, not long after he fell dangerouſly ſicke; and (to be briefe) <hi>Baptiſmi infuſionem accepit, &amp;c.</hi> he was baptized, as he lay ſicke in his bed (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Euſeb. Ib.</note>) if a man may ſay, that ſuch a fellow were capable of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: but after his recouerie (ſaith <hi>Cornelius</hi>) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not thoſe bleſſings, <hi>Quae iuxta Eccleſiae Canonem conſequi oportebat,</hi> which hee ought to haue receiued according to the Canons of the Church. And what were they? <hi>Obſignationem ab Epiſcopo collatam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Ibid:</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation from the Biſhop, that hee wanted. And then he infers, <hi>Quum autem illa potitus non ſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How this phraſe of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſee §. 65. &amp;c. &amp; §. 71</note> 
               <hi>quomodo (quaeſo) Spiritum Sanctum adeptus eſt?</hi> Since he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Confirmation, by what meanes did he obtaine the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p n="61">61 Out of which words we may gather two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſeruations. 1. That by a Canon of the Church in the more perfect times, <hi>Confirmation</hi> was <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to follow after Baptiſme,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> hath it) to be ſigned and croſſed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. 2. That <hi>Confirmation</hi> was held the <hi>ordinarie meanes,</hi> whereby we receiue the holy Ghoſt, <hi>ad aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, &amp; robur,</hi> to the enceaſe, &amp; ſtrength of faith.</p>
            <p n="62">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15174:19"/>62 But me thinkes I heare, ſome one or other ſay, <hi>Durum eſt, abſurdum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, ferri non poteſt,</hi> this an hard, an abſurd ſaying; and not to be endured: for it is much preiudiciall to Baptiſme, and ſeemes to derogate from the power of that Sacrament: and a man may (perchance) now (as ſome in former times) obiect againſt Confirmation, in behalfe (as it were) of Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſ. hom. in Pent. ad Populum,</note> 
               <hi>Quid mihi prodeſt poſt myſterium baptiſmatis miniſterium confirma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis?</hi> What profit haue I by <hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands?</hi> What vſe is there of Confirmation after Baptiſme, and the myſteries of Baptiſme? <hi>Quantum video non totum de fonte ſuſcepimus, ſi poſt fontem adie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione nout generis indigemus?</hi> as farre as I perceiue, we haue not receiued our Chriſtendome fully from the font, if after Baptiſme we neede the addition of ſome new grace: which (it ſeemes) we doe, if <hi>certaine graces and gifts of the holy Ghoſt</hi> be aſcribed to Confirmation as proper to it.</p>
            <p n="63">63 We confeſſe indeed in Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> phraſe, <hi>non toleratur, niſi intelligatur;</hi> that phraſe of <hi>Cornelius</hi> is not to be endured, vnleſſe it be rightly vnderſtood: let vs heare therefore <hi>Euſebius Emiſ.</hi> (who liued within the firſt fiue hundred yeares) and ſee whether he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a ſufficient expoſition of it, and an anſwer to this obiection. Behold, he tels vs, that this addition of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation doth no way derogate from baptiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Emiſ. hom. in Pent.</note> or the vertue of Baptiſme. <hi>Sic enim exigit militaris or do,</hi> this courſe, this order is obſerued amongſt militarie men, (and the Church is militant here on earth) when the Generall of an army hath entertained a freſh Souldier
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15174:19"/> into his company, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n ſolum ſignat recepsum, ſed etiam armis competentibus inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uit pugnaturum:</hi> He doth not onely ſigne him with his badge, or colours, but he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes him too with ſuch weapons, as are fitting for a man of armes. So (ſaith hee) to a man, that is ſigned with Chriſts colours, that is baptiſed before,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>benedic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio illa</hi> that bleſſing of Confirmation, <hi>munitio</hi> eſt, is a guard or defence, and ſerues inſteed of armor againſt the enemy. Haſt thou preſſed, haſt thou ſigned (ſayth he) a ſouldier for Gods battels? Giue him alſo thoſe neceſſaries, which are requiſite for ſuch a ſeruice. Is it enough (thinke you) for a father to leaue his infant childe a goodly portion, if he labor not alſo to prouide him a faithfull guardian?<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Paracletus regeneratis in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto &amp; conſolator, &amp; tutor eſt: the holy Ghoſt</hi> (ſayth <hi>Emiſ.</hi>) is both a <hi>Comforter and a guardian</hi> to all thoſe who are regenerate in Chriſt Ieſus, and theſe offices he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="64">64 <hi>The holy Ghoſt</hi> therefore beares his part both in <hi>Baptiſme and in Confirmation;</hi> but with diuers effects, <hi>Spiritus enim ſanctus, qui ſuper aquas Baptiſmi ſalutifero deſcendit illapſu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Emiſ. Ibid.</note> for the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> (who deſcends vpon the waters of Baptiſme with a ſauing grace) giues <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of innocencie at the Font;</hi> but <hi>in Confirmation</hi> hee giues <hi>ſtrength and increaſe of grace. In Baptiſme</hi> he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generates</hi> vs to life; after Baptiſme hee <hi>Confirmes, hee armes</hi> vs for the battell. <hi>In baptiſme</hi> he doth <hi>nouriſh</hi> vs, after Baptiſme <hi>in Confirmation</hi> hee doth <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> vs. And ſo the bleſſings of Baptiſme are ſufficient for all thoſe, who are ready to depart this mortall life: but for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15174:20"/> them, that liue longer, the aſſiſtance of <hi>Confirmation</hi> is <hi>very neceſſary. Baptiſme</hi> of it ſelfe <hi>(without Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)</hi> ſaueth them, who are inſtantly to be receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the peace of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but <hi>confirmation</hi> doth furniſh, &amp; arme all thoſe, who are reſerued for the bitter agonies, and dangerous battels, which are ſought in this vale of miſerie,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> this world of temptation. But he which after Baptiſme dyes immaculate in the innocency acquired in Baptiſme, hath his <hi>confirmation in death, confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur morte, quia iam non poteſt peccare poſt mortem,</hi> he is <hi>confirmed in death,</hi> becauſe after death he can ſinne no more. Thus farre <hi>Emiſſenus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">65 This was the opinion of thoſe primitiue times, and this gaue occaſion to <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, to ſay of that heretick <hi>Nouatus,</hi> who was neuer <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Cum illa potitus non ſit, &amp;c.</hi> ſince he enioyed not <hi>Confirmation</hi> (that is, would not be confirmed) by what meanes (thinke you) did hee receiue the holy Ghoſt (as he is giuen in confirmation?)</p>
            <p n="66">66 For although <hi>the effects of the holy Ghoſt be very admirable,</hi> and <hi>diuine in Baptiſme,</hi> yet in eſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the <hi>H. Ghoſt</hi> is appropriated to <hi>Confirmation.</hi> For in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> our <hi>regeneration</hi> is eſpecially <hi>attributed to Chriſt,</hi> by whoſe blood wee are waſhed, and cleanſed from our ſinnes; but in <hi>Confirmation</hi> the eſpeciall effects thereof are aſcribed to the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> Not but that the whole Trinitie workes both in the one, and in the other: but that we might the better diſtinguiſh, and diſcerne the diuerſitie of graces, and acknowledge the diſtinction of perſons, therefore <hi>Confirmation</hi> is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15174:20"/> by <hi>Impoſition of hands, and giuing the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme by waſhing</hi> (through the blood of Chriſt) in <hi>in the name of the Father the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">67. For (as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> notes excellently) when the Sonne of God (the ſecond perſon) had bin conuerſant amongſt vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> corporally: fit it was alſo that the holy Ghoſt (the third perſon) ſhould appeare vnto vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a bodily ſhape;<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. Orat. in Peut.</note> and when the Sonne of God departed from vs, then it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Ghoſt to deſcend vnto vs, that ſo the H. Ghoſt and his bleſſed operations might be knowne to the world no leſſe, then our Sauior was, &amp; his marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and worthy effects, &amp; both diſtinguiſhed the one from the other; which cauſed the Fathers to make dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the effects in the meanes &amp; working of our ſaluation, aſcribing eſpecially the effects of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to Chriſt, &amp; the effects of <hi>confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the H. ghoſt,</hi> eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming both conuenient, and requiſit, for euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, before he be admitted to the holy communion.</p>
            <p n="68">68 <hi>Euthymius</hi> therfore treating vpon thoſe words of our Sauiour (<hi>Si non abiero, Paracletus non veniet ad vos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euthym. in Ioh. 16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vnleſſe I go from you, the Comforter will not come vnto you: but if I depart from you,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.17.</note> I will ſend him to you) tels vs, that it was decreed by God from al eternity, that euery one of the 3 perſons in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould do ſomthing for the procuring mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and performe (as it were) a ſeuerall office euery one of them. The <hi>Father</hi> ſent the ſonne and drew di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to the ſonne; the <hi>Sonne</hi> taught, redeemed, and ſet man at liberty: the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> dayly perfits, <hi>confirmes</hi> &amp; ſanctifies man. <hi>Suas cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vices fuiſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euthym. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ſuum cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tempus
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15174:21"/> ſuam quemque egiſſe perſonam:</hi> In this great buſineſſe of our ſaluation euery perſon had his turne, euery one his time, and euery one acted (as it were) his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For although the whole Trinitie (ſayth <hi>Schluſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi>) doth ioyntly worke the redemption of man (as holy Scripture teaches) <hi>tamen cuiuſque perſonae proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas obſeruatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Schluſſel. de Stancar. p. 52.</note> yet in this generall worke the particular proprietie of euery perſon is obſerued, and the <hi>Sonne onely</hi> is ordained our <hi>Mediator and Redeemer:</hi> thus in like manner, though the grace of <hi>Confirmation</hi> is wrought in vs by the whole Trinitie, yet (we ſee) the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> is termed in Scripture <hi>our Comforter and Confirmer.</hi> To the one both Scriptures, and Fathers attribute the vertue of Baptiſme, to the other the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditie of Confirmation: and hence (it may bee) it is, that Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Act. 8.16.</note> that <hi>the holy Ghoſt was come down on none of the Samaritans, but they were baptiſed onely in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Whereby he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the proper effects both of the <hi>Sonne</hi> and of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> attributing the <hi>effects of Baptiſme to the Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>grace of Confirmation to the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and yet we know by Scripture, that the holy Ghoſt was, and is giuen both in the one, and in the other: and the Samaritans baptiſme in the name of the Lord Ieſus was not voyde of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="69">69 This diuerſitie of receiuing the holy Ghoſt in Baptiſme and in Confirmation, <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerues, and diſtinguiſheth in this manner. In Baptiſme (ſayth he) <hi>Recipit quis illum Dei ſpiritum, &amp;c.</hi> man receiues that Spirit of God,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Bapt. c. 5.</note> which in the creation he receiued
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15174:21"/> from the breath of God, but loſt afterward by his fall. <hi>Non quod in aquis</hi> (ſayth <hi>Tertullian) Spiritum ſanctum conſequamur, ſed in aqua emundati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. c 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſub Angelo ſpiritui ſancto praeparamur:</hi> not that we receiue the holy Ghoſt in the waters of Baptiſme, but being cleanſed by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we are prepared by the Angell to receiue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. He hath reference to the Angell in the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid c. 5.</note> which was a type of our Chriſtian Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; as he notes before.</p>
            <p n="70">70 After this, ſpeaking of confirmation, hee ſayth, <hi>Dehinc manus imponitur, per benedictionem aduocans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>et inuitans ſpiritum ſanctum,</hi> after Baptiſme followes <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> (that is, <hi>Confirmation</hi>) by benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and bleſſing vs, calling and inuiting the holy Ghoſt to come downe vpon vs: and then expreſſing the manner by a pretty ſimile of ſome winde and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtruments (but to mee as yet ſomewhat obſcure) he concludes the poynt with this queſtion:<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Non licebit Deo in ſuo organo per manus ſanctas ſublimitatem modu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari ſpiritalem?</hi> Is it not lawfull for God to modulate, or tune in man (who is his owne organ or inſtrument) an high and ſpirituall note by Impoſition of holy hands? He meanes the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, which are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a ſublime and high meaſure in Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="71">71 We muſt not conceiue either by thoſe words of <hi>Cornelius</hi> concerning <hi>Nouatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. 6. c. 42.</note> (<hi>Cum obſignatione ab Epiſcopo non ſit potitus, etc.</hi> ſince the Biſhop neuer <hi>confirmed him,</hi> how could he receiue the holy Ghoſt?) or by theſe of <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de Baptiſt c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.</note> (<hi>Non in aquis ſpiritum ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſequimur,</hi> wee receiue not the holy Ghoſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15174:22"/> that the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, power, or effects of the H. Ghoſt are ſecluded from Baptiſme; (God forbid, wee ſhould thinke ſo;) but we muſt conſider, that in theſe, and the like words of thoſe reuerend Fathers, there is onely a diuerſity noted of the operations of the holy Spirit: which (as they thought) were more obſeruable in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, confirmation adding a farther degree of grace to the grace receiued in Baptiſme. This is plain by certaine paſſages of <hi>Tertul.</hi> for hee cals the waters of Baptiſme, <hi>priſtinam ſedem ſpiritus ſancti,</hi> the ancient ſeat of the he holy Ghoſt, as may be ſeene in the ſame book:<note place="margin">Ibid. c. 8.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>Tunc</hi> then, that is, <hi>in confirmation</hi> after baptiſme, <hi>ille ſanctiſsimus ſpiritus ſuper emundata, et benedicta corpora libens à patre deſcendit,</hi> the moſt H. ſpirit deſcends willingly from the Father vpon thoſe cleanſed, &amp; bleſſed bodies by baptiſme, <hi>et ſuper baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi aquas, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſtina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recognoſcens, conquieſcit,</hi> &amp; ſettles himſelf vpon the waters of baptiſme (that is) vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are baptiſed, acknowledging (as it were) his ancient &amp; former place. This (though perchance <hi>Tertul.</hi> had a farther reference) may bee vnderſtood as well of theſe waters of baptiſme, wherby all Chriſtians are cleanſed, as of the waters of Iordan, wherin Chriſt was baptiſed: for that indeede is <hi>priftina ſedes</hi> the firſt &amp; ancient ſeat of the H. Ghoſt, which is ſtill continued in the Church of Chriſt by the waters of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="72">72 Now <hi>Caiet.</hi> is of opinion, that the H. Ghoſt deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded twiſe vpon our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Caict. in Euan Ioh. c. 1.</note> once in Baptiſme, &amp; once after Baptiſme, &amp; <hi>Barradius</hi> ſaith, it had bin a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable opinion,<note place="margin">Barrad.</note> ſo he had brought authoritie for it out of Scriptures, or Fathers. Firſt (ſaith <hi>Caiet.</hi>) the holy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15174:22"/> Ghoſt deſcended vpon Chriſt <hi>in</hi> or <hi>at</hi> the time of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. <hi>Io.</hi> 1. for <hi>the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming downe of the H. Ghoſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vpon him,</hi> was the token which was giuen S <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1 32.</note> wherby hee ſhould know Chriſt <hi>ſenſibiliter et determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natè</hi> ſenſibly in particular, whom before he knew onely <hi>intelligibiliter et in generali,</hi> in his vnderſtanding by ſome generall notions;<note place="margin">Caiet. &amp;. Lyra in locum.</note> that ſuch a one there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, he knew before; but which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man was he, till now he knew not: &amp; yet it is playne <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. that the Baptiſt knew Chriſt, when he layd his hands vpon him to baptiſe him; for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> put him backe, ſaying, I haue neede to be baptiſed of thee,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.14.</note> and comeſt thou to me? By which words it appeares eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> knew Chriſt at the inſtant of bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him: and <hi>Pererius</hi> profeſſeth,<note place="margin">Perer. in c. 1. Euan Ioh. Diſput. 48:</note> that the Baptiſt knew not Chriſt otherwiſe, then by the holy Ghoſt lighting and remaining vpon him. The holy Ghoſt therefore deſcended viſibly vpon Chriſt, before Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> knew him to be the Chriſt; and that deſcending was <hi>in, or at the time of his Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="73">73 2. After baptiſme the H. Ghoſt deſcended vpon Ieſus, as is to be ſeene in three former Euangeliſts, for there it is ſayd, that the holy Ghoſt came downe vpon Ieſus, when he was come out of the water,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.16. Mar. 1.10. Luc. 3.22.</note> after hee had beene baptiſed, And this latter comming down of the holy Ghoſt ſeemes to be inſtead of confirmation; which is not any new imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but is grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Optatus</hi> opinion, who was (in S. <hi>Auſt.</hi> iudgment) <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabilis memoriae, et Catholicae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munionis Epiſcopus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. Ep. Parmen. l. 1. c. 3,</note> a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of reuerend memorie, &amp; of the Catholick co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15174:23"/> or religion. And this Catholicke Biſhop <hi>Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Optat Milcu cont Parm. l. 4</note> 
               <hi>Apertum eſt coelum D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> patre vngente, ſpiritale olcum deſcendit in imagine columbae, et inſedit capiti eius, et perfudit eum:</hi> The heauens opened, God the Farher annoynting him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> the ſpirituall oyle deſcended in the ſhape of a Doue, &amp; ſate vpon his head, &amp; ouer ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, or (if I may ſo ſay) ouerſhadowed him. And then he addes, <hi>Cui ne impoſitio manus deſuiſſe videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>vox audita eſt Dei de nube dicentis, Hic eſt filius meus de quo bene ſenſi:</hi> leſt <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> ſhould ſeeme to be wanting to Chriſt, the voyce of God was heard from the cloude, ſaying: This is my beloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> Which voyce was heard (according to <hi>Caietan</hi>) at the ſecond apparition of the holy Ghoſt. Which double apparition (it may bee) is the ſame with that of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> 
               <hi>deſcending, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining.</hi> Whereby it may ſeeme, that <hi>Ieſus</hi> himſelfe was both the <hi>Author, and partaker</hi> of thoſe three great and bleſſed myſteries, <hi>Baptiſme, Confirmation,</hi> and the holy <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="74">74 So then (you ſee) according to <hi>Optatus</hi> opinion, <hi>Confirmation</hi> is not only more ancient then preaching to the Gentiles (as heretofore hath beene manifeſted) but it hath the beginning not long after Baptiſme, &amp; before Chriſts preaching to the Iewes; for hee was baptiſed before he preached;<note place="margin">Mat. 4 17.</note> thats plaine.</p>
            <p n="75">75 But to returne, it is euident alſo by another place of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that he held, that the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> was <hi>giuen in Baptiſme:</hi> for diſputing againſt <hi>Marcion</hi> hee ſayth, firſt, that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is the Sacrament of Faith.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15174:23"/> Secondly, The remiſſion of ſinne. Thirdly,<note place="margin">Tertul. cont. Marcionem. l. 1. c. 38.</note> the abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from death. Fourthly, the regeneration of man: and laſtly, <hi>Conſecutio ſpiritus ſancti,</hi> the <hi>obtaining of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Hereby it appeares, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, that the holy Ghoſt was firſt <hi>gotten in,</hi> or <hi>giuen by Baptiſme:</hi> whoſe operation though it were auaylea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Baptiſme, yet <hi>in Confirmation</hi> it was held <hi>more effectuall</hi> for ſome other ends,<note place="margin">Tert. de Baptiſ. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſublimitatem modulando ſpiritalem,</hi> by ſtretching forth his gifts to higher ſtraines.</p>
            <p n="76">76 And this high conceit of the fruites and effects of Confirmation ſo preuayled in thoſe times, that Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> (as it ſeemes) ranked <hi>Baptiſme and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation in the ſame order,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cip. Epiſt 76 ad Steph.</note> calling them both Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or myſteries in a large ſenſe, &amp; held them both neceſſary for a Chriſtian, if both might be had conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently: for hauing occaſion to ſpeake of ſuch, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from hereſie to the Catholicke Church, and maintaining, that they ought to be rebaptiſed (which at that time was the African error) when ſome other thought it ſufficient, to haue them <hi>confirmed by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands,</hi> without rebaptiſing them: he would not yeeld vnto it, but ſayd, <hi>Tunc demum plene ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, &amp; eſſe filii Dei poſſunt, ſi Sacramento vtroque naſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> then may theſe hereticks be fully ſanctified, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſons of God, if they bee borne again of both the Sacraments (namely of Baptiſme, and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:) for he held the Baptiſme of hereticks to bee no Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="77">77 The ſame ſentence was deliuered by <hi>Neme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:15174:24"/> one of the Biſhops, who were preſent at the Councell of Carthage, where this queſtion was venti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated of rebaptizing hereticks:<note place="margin">Apud. Cyp. de haeret bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandis.</note> 
               <hi>Manifeſtumeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vtro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſacramento debere eos renaſci in Eccleſia Catholicae,</hi> It is manifeſt, that all they, who returne from hereſie, muſt be borne anew of both the Sacraments (meaning Baptiſme &amp; Confirmation) in the Catholick church. For,<note place="margin">Hooker Eccl. pol. l. 5. §. 50.</note> 
               <hi>in the writings of the ancient Fathers,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> well obſerues, <hi>all the articles which are peculiar to Chriſtian faith, all duties of religion containing that, which ſenſe, or naturall reaſon cannot of it ſelfe diſcerne, are moſt commonly named Sacraments:</hi> and ſo I vnderſtand <hi>Sacraments</hi> through all this ſermon. For though the Fathers,<note place="margin">Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in Eph. 4 tract. Quid ſit Eccleſia.</note> and ſome late writers call <hi>Confirmation</hi> a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, yet it is <hi>not a Sacrament rightly ſo called,</hi> as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Lords Supper are; becauſe there is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>verbum et elementu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex inſtitutione domini,</hi> the word and element ſet downe by the inſtitution of Chriſt, which the other two haue: and therefore wee terme thoſe <hi>myſteries</hi> (but <hi>not</hi> properly <hi>Sacraments</hi>) which haue a Ceremonie, but not an element, neither <hi>verba formalia</hi> expreſſe formall words appointed by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; both which are neceſſarily required (as <hi>Thomas</hi> teacheth) to a Sacrament rightly, and properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Firſt, there muſt be <hi>Verba determinata</hi> (ſayth hee) poſitiue words determined by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Tho. 3 c. 66. 7. c.</note> which are (as it were) the forme of the Sacrament. Secondly, there muſt be <hi>res</hi> the matter (as it is called) of the Sacrament and that muſt be <hi>determinata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid 5. c.</note> ſuch onely as hath beene inſtituted &amp; enioyned by Chriſt himſelfe. We eſteeme
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15174:24"/> not therefore any other element (though named by the Fathers, and vſed in the primitiue and Apoſtolick times) fit to be called a Sacrament,<note place="margin">Ib q 72. 1. 1.</note> when it is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by words of our Sauiour; for that alſo muſt be <hi>res determinata,</hi> a determinate matter, or element ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Chriſt for that holy ende; in whoſe power onely it is to conſtitute a Sacrament, and to appoint both <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>forme,</hi> that is both <hi>word</hi> and <hi>element;</hi> without both which <hi>Sacramentum proprie dictum</hi> a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament properly ſo called cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p n="78">78 This conſideration moued ſome of the more ancient ſchoolemen (as <hi>Caſſander</hi> obſerues) to number onely two Sacraments, which they call <hi>Sacramenta propriè dicta,</hi> namely, <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſſan, conſul. art. 13.</note> becauſe they two onely haue <hi>verbum &amp; elementum ex diuina inſtitutione determinata,</hi> both word and element ordeyned by Chriſt, who is both God and man. The firſt, that euer reckoned (ſayth he) vpon ſeuen Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was <hi>Peter Lombard;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and ſince that time the Schoolemen are become <hi>iurati in verba magiſtri,</hi> ſo wedded, and (as it were) ſworne to that fond opinion of the Maſter of the Sentences, that they forget their grounds, and contradict their own principles, as might be ſhewed at large. But (I feare) I haue already digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to much, <hi>Nunc itaque recurrat ſtylus ad ſuam mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid ad Eugen. l 2. c. 1.</note> (as ſometimes Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayd) <hi>&amp; in eo quo propoſueramus, ſuo tramite gradiatur oratio,</hi> let vs now therefore returne to the matter wee had in hand, and ſee (as order requires) what reaſon Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> giues for his opinion, concerning the neceſſitie (which hee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15174:25"/> ſeemes to imply) of Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="79">79 The reaſon he giues, is that ſaying of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.5</note> 
               <hi>Niſi quis renatus fuerit, &amp;c. Except a man bee borne againe of water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God:</hi> which he interprets thus; Except a man be borne againe of water (in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi>) and by the Spirit, or the holy Ghoſt, (in <hi>Confirmation</hi>) he canot enter into the kingdome of God. This ſence ſeemes to haue beene receiued in thoſe times, and continued long after in the Church of Chriſt; for you may reade the ſame interpretation in a ſermon of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb.</hi>
               <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. in do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Poſt Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ,</note> 
               <hi>Emiſ.</hi> who liued about 200. yeares after S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="80">80 And S. <hi>Auſt.</hi> prouing againſt the Nouatians; that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was baptized, ſeemes to fauour the ſame interpretation: for he ſaith, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles were baptized before the time, that S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> denied his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. but <hi>nondum confirmati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they were not as yet <hi>confirmed</hi> by the holy Ghoſt, who appeared vnto them on the day of Pentecoſt; neither were they <hi>confirmed</hi> by that inſpiration of our Sauiour, when hee breathed on them, ſaying, <hi>Receiue the holy Ghoſt: Vnde recte dici poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.</note> from whence (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine</hi>) we may ſafely conclude, that when S. <hi>Peter</hi> denyed his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, <hi>Nondum fuerant Apoſtoli baptizati, non tamen aqua, ſed ſpiritu ſancto,</hi> the Apoſtles were not then baptized; baptized they were with water, but they were not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the holy Ghoſt, (that is, <hi>Confirmed</hi>) And yet S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> is of opinion, that the Apoſtles were baptized with the baptiſme of Chriſt.<note place="margin">A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ib.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="81">81 This expoſition of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (vpon thoſe words
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15174:25"/> of our Sauiour, <hi>Niſi quis renatu, fuerit, &amp;c.</hi> though it be not now commonly receiued, is far more probable, &amp; much more agreeable to the Analogie of faith,<note place="margin">Cip. Epiſt 76 ad Steph.</note> &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the firſt Church, then that late conſtruction of ſome Noueliſts; who take water in that ſentence of our Sauior by a Metaphor, or borrowed ſpeech <hi>for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God,</hi> the effect wherof (ſay they) it ſhadowes out; ſo that, as <hi>by water and the ſpirit</hi> ſome vnderſtand <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme onely,</hi> theſe men vnderſtand not baptiſme, but <hi>the Spirit of God onely,</hi> which cleanſeth the filth of ſin,<note place="margin">T. C. l. 1. p. 143</note> and cooleth the boyling heate of an vnquiet conſcience, as water waſheth the thing that is foule, and quencheth the heate of the fire. So <hi>Cartwr.</hi> that he may diſcredit the vſe, and neceſſitie of priuate Baptiſme. But we hold it for an infallible rule in expoſition of Scripture,<note place="margin">Hooker Eccleſ. poſ l. 5. §. 59,</note> that <hi>where a litterall conſtruction will ſtand, the fartheſt from the letter is commonly the worſt.</hi> And thoſe Fathers had for their defence the phraſe of Scripture, which vnder the name of <hi>water</hi> onely (without adding the Spirit) ſometimes ſignifies the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note> as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are ſaid to be borne anew, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> euen of water: for S. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches vs,<note place="margin">Eph: 5.26,</note> that God by <hi>water</hi> doth purifie, &amp; cleanſe his Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> purging with water by the word: viz. <hi>In the name of the Father, the Son, and the H. Ghoſt.</hi> But they had moſt eſpecially theſe words of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> for their warrant, <hi>Repent and be baptiſed, &amp;c. for the remiſsion of ſins, and yee ſhall receiue the gift of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.38.</note> Where by the word <hi>Baptiſed</hi> is ſignified the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>baptiſm;</hi> by <hi>Remiſsion of ſinnes</hi> iuſtifying grace: and by the gift
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15174:26"/> 
               <hi>of the holy Ghoſt Confirmation</hi> is meant; or ſome ſuch gift, or gifts, as were giuen at the Pentecoſt, and were receiued <hi>poſt baptiſmum per manus Impoſitionem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caiet. in locum</note> (as <hi>Caietan</hi> notes) after baptiſme by Impoſition of hands: which place ſeemes to bee parallel with that <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5. but yet that vſuall interpretation of thoſe words of our Sauiour <hi>(Niſi quis renatus fuerit, &amp;c.)</hi> is moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke which expounds it of Baptiſme onely: where in is both <hi>water,</hi> as a dutie required on our parts, and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> as a gift, which God beſtoweth for his part on all thoſe, that are baptiſed. This latter expoſition is generally receiued, and conſtantly embraced by the whole Church: and that interpretation of Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> which ſeemes to imply, that Confirmation is neceſſary to ſaluation, is thus mollified by the Schools.</p>
            <p n="82">82 Confirmation (ſay they) is neceſſary, <hi>quia ſine ea non habetur finis ita conuenienter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. 3. q. 65. 4 c.</note> becauſe we cannot attaine our propoſed ende, which is eternall life, ſo conueniently without it. Others tels vs, that it is not <hi>ſimpliciter neceſſaria</hi> ſimply neceſſary:<note place="margin">Suarez. in 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 8 ib. in 12. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>up. 38. lect. 1</note> but yet it is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria ad melius eſſe</hi> neceſſary for our <hi>better being</hi> in Chriſtianitie, that is, <hi>valdè vtilis eſt ad ſalutem, &amp; ad perſeuerandum in fide,</hi> Confirmation is very commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to make vs perſeuere in the true faith, and very profitable to further our ſaluation. Some other againe ſay, that Confirmation is of neceſſitie in this ſenſe to ſaluation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12. Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Non quod per illud conferatur aliquid, ſine quo non ſit aditus ad vitamaeternam,</hi> not that any thing is beſtowed <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> Confirmation, without which the entrance is barred to eternall life: for that grace is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15174:26"/> conferred in Baptiſme, <hi>quae facit dignos vita aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> which makes vs worthy of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; <hi>ſed eſt neceſsitatis, id eſt, neceſſarium eſt, vt non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnatur, quia ſi contemnitur, non eſt aditus ad vitamae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam:</hi> but though Confirmation be not of neceſſitie in that ſenſe, yet it is ſo neceſſary, that it may not bee contemned, for if we contemne it, <hi>contempt</hi> will cut off our paſſage to euerlaſting bliſſe. Some ſuch ſenſe as this our Church entertaineth, which requireth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to be had, before wee receiue the holy Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, according to the cuſtome of the Primitiue times: which cuſtome being ioyned with the law of our Church makes the practiſe thereof neceſſary, and the contempt very dangerous: for, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>Contemptus in omne ſpecie mandatorum pariponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re grauis, &amp; communiter damnabilis eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Praecep. &amp; Diſpen, c: 12.</note> 
               <hi>Contempt</hi> in all kinde of precepts (whether they bee the precepts of God or man, ſaith he, whether they be fixed or muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) is alike waighty, and commonly damnable. Hee ſpeakes of all ſuch precepts, as are not contrary to the word of God: and though hee holds the <hi>contempt</hi> of theſe conſtitutions to be <hi>damnable,</hi> yet he eſteems the <hi>neglect</hi> to be but <hi>culpable:</hi> and his reaſon is,<note place="margin">Ibid. c. 14.</note> becauſe <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> proceeds oft times from ignorance, or weakneſſe, but the other <hi>aut odioſae pertinaciae eſt, aut contumaciae non ferendae,</hi> contempt breakes forth either from odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pertinacie, or intollerable contumacie: and then (ſayth he) <hi>non peccati ſpecies, ſed peccantis intentiopen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatur,</hi> the offence it ſelfe is not ſo much to be regarded, as the entent of the offendor to be reſpected. Shortly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15174:27"/> after concluding this point, he reſolues thus, <hi>Si volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; non poſſumus, ſecuri ſumus; ſi poſſumus, et nolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperbi ſumus;</hi> If we would performe thoſe duties, which are required at our hands, and cannot, our deſire ſecures vs; but if we can, and will not, wee are proud: and you know how dangerous pride is by the fall of Lucifer.</p>
            <p n="83">83 And that the holy Ghoſt may bee giuen in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers meaſure, &amp; to diuers purpoſes: firſt, in <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> Secondly, in <hi>Confirmation:</hi> and thirdly, at taking of <hi>Orders,</hi> may appeare by the diuers manner, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſeaſons, and ends, wherein, and whereto the Apoſtles receiued the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Greg. Nazian.</hi> ſaith, that the holy Ghoſt was giuen to the Apoſtles three ſundry times,<note place="margin">Greg Naz. orat. in Pent.</note> and withall in three ſundry meaſures: 1. Before Chriſts paſſion. 2. After his reſurrection; and laſtly, after his aſcenſion.</p>
            <p n="84">84 1. <hi>Before the paſsion,</hi> when our Sauiour gaue them power to cure diſeaſes, and to caſt out Deuils, which they performed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith <hi>Nazian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>) not without aſſiſtance of the holy Spirit. Or elſe he was giuen them (as ſome thinke) in their Baptiſme; which appeares by that of our Sauiour, who ſaid to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">Io. 13.10:</note> 
               <hi>Qui lotus eſt, etc.</hi> He that is waſhed, needes not ſaue to waſh his feete, but is cleane euery whit: for ſo <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> vnderſtands that text,<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. 108. ad Seleuc.</note> viz. of the holy Ghoſt cleanſing the Apoſtles by Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="85">85. 2. <hi>After his reſurrection,</hi> when he breathed on them,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.22.</note> and ſaide vnto them, <hi>Receiue the holy Ghoſt:</hi> at which time hee ſanctified them, but did not perfit
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15174:27"/> them. Thirdly, <hi>After his aſcenſion</hi> in the Pentecoſt, when that promiſe of Chriſt was fulfilled, which hee made <hi>Act.</hi> 1. (ye ſhall receiue <hi>virtutem ſuperuenient is ſpiritus ſancti,</hi> the power of the holy Ghoſt, which ſhall come on you) which is vnderſtood not onely of the gift of miracles, and tongues,<note place="margin">Leo epiſt. 37 c. 2. Leoni Epiſ. Rauen.</note> but of other gifts and <hi>vertues</hi> eſpecially, which are giuen in Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith, <hi>Per Epiſcopalem manuum impoſitionem virtus ſpiritus confertur,</hi> the <hi>vertue</hi> or <hi>power</hi> of the ſpirit is conferred by <hi>Epiſcopall impoſition of hands,</hi> that is, in <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="86">86 The firſt of theſe times (ſaith <hi>Nazian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in Pentec-</note>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the holy Ghoſt was but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> obſcurely in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, at the ſecond time <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> more expreſſely, more manifeſtly: but in the third time <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> more perfectly: for now he was not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent in in them by his efficacy, and power as he was before, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eſſentially: which hee himſelfe excellently expeſſeth in this manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if a man ſhould ſay, that the holy Ghoſt was conuerſant with the Apoſtles as a familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that he ioyned with them in gouerning the ſtate of the Church.</p>
            <p n="87">87 And as <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth a threefold manner, and meaſure in impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the holy Ghoſt to the Apoſtles: one manner was <hi>inuiſibly</hi> at their Baptiſme, as he is now giuen to vs: but the other two were <hi>viſibly,</hi> and <hi>manifeſtly: Manifeſtam enim impertionem ſpiritus ſancti</hi> (ſaith Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine) <hi>non ſemel ſed bis numero Dominus egit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 14. in Euan. Iohan.</note> the Lord
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15174:28"/> wrought the manifeſt beſtowing of the holy Ghoſt, not once onely, but twice, at two ſeuerall times: once when hee breathed vpon them after his reſurrection: which (as ſome ſay) was onely <hi>viſibili modo</hi> after a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner: but the other, at the Pentecoſt, was <hi>viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter,</hi> in a viſible forme: for the holy Ghoſt was ſeene to deſcend vpon them <hi>viſibly</hi> in clouen tongues.</p>
            <p n="88">88 And to theſe ſundry manners, were ioyned ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry meaſures of imparting the holy Ghoſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſay very truly (diſtinguiſhing the times, and meaſures) that the Apoſtles had the holy Ghoſt (when they were baptiſed), and yet they had not the holy Ghoſt, before our Sauiour breathed on them (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection) <hi>quia quantum habendus fuerat</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine) nondum habebant,</hi> becauſe they had him not as yet in that meaſure, as they were to haue him. <hi>Habebant itaque minus, dandus erateis amplius</hi> they had him indeed in a leſſe manner,<note place="margin">Aug. Ibid.</note> but he was to be giuen them in a larger meaſure: <hi>habebant occulte, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepturi erant manifeſte;</hi> they had him <hi>hiddenly,</hi> but they were to receiue him <hi>minifeſtly:</hi> for that was one gift of the holy Ghoſt, to make it manifeſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they had the H. Ghoſt: and thefore the H. Ghoſt was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, not onely to them, that had him not, but to thoſe alſo,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that had him already, and that <hi>non incaſſum</hi> not in vaine; <hi>non habenti quidem vt habeatur, habenti autem, vt amplius habeatur,</hi> to him that hath not the holy Ghoſt, that he may haue him; and to him that hath, that hee may haue the holy ſpirit in a greater meaſure: thus <hi>in baptiſme</hi> the holy Ghoſt is giuen to him, that hath him not, that ſo he may haue him: but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15174:28"/> 
               <hi>in Confirmation</hi> he is giuen to him, that hath him alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that he may haue him more.</p>
            <p n="89">89 For except there were diuers meaſures of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the holy Ghoſt, the Prophet <hi>Elizeus</hi> would not haue ſayde, <hi>ſpiritus, qui in te eſt, duplex ſit in me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.9.</note> let the ſpirit, which is in thee, be double in me.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> When Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt ſayd, God giues not the Spirit by meaſure, hee ſpoke it of the Sonne of God, to whom the ſpirit was not giuen in any meaſure,<note place="margin">coloſſ. 2.9:</note> becauſe <hi>in him all the fulneſſe of the Deitie inhabited.</hi> But to all other the holy Ghoſt is giuen in a certaine meaſure, and after he is once giuen, is added againe, and doth <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruenire</hi> come again vpon them in <hi>confirmation,</hi> as he did <hi>ſuperuenire</hi> come again vpon the Apoſtles, when Chriſt breathed vpon them: and againe at the <hi>Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt.</hi> Thus is he <hi>giuen againe and againe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 74 in Euang. Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and added vnto vs, <hi>donec vnicuique pro modo ſuae perfectionis propria me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura compleatur,</hi> vntill euery mans proper meaſure bee filled, according to the manner of his perfection; and therefore when we ſay, that confirmation is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or that it giues vs perfection, we meane not abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but ſuch a perfection, as wee are capable of;<note place="margin">Ro. 12:3:</note> which is after one meaſure in one, and in a diuers mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in another. Wherefore the Apoſtle exhorteth vs not to thinke more highly of our ſelues, then wee ought: but to thinke ſoberly, according as God hath dealt to euery man the meaſure of faith (or of the H Spirit): not that the H. Ghoſt is parted amongſt vs, <hi>neque enim ipſe diuiditur Spiritus, ſed dona per Spiritum,</hi> for the Spirit cannot be diuided, but the gifts
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15174:29"/> are diuided, or diuerſly beſtowed by the ſpirit: and therefore the ſame Apoſtle ſayth; that there are <hi>diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones donationum</hi> diuerſitie of gifts,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.3:</note> but one ſpirit onely. This is the doctrine of Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="90">90 From this diuerſitie of the gifts, and operations of the holy Ghoſt in the ſame perſons, at the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of ſeuerall myſteries, the ſchoole ſeems to haue borrowed that acute diſtinction of three ſundry mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of thoſe gifts of the holy ghoſt, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in the Church of Chriſt: for (ſay they) there is <hi>Spiritus ſancti Infuſio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rich de S. Vr d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. Serm. de Spirit. S.</note> 
               <hi>Diffuſio, Effuſio,</hi> Infuſion, Diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Effuſion of the holy Spirit. 1. <hi>Infuſion</hi> is, when leſſe liquor is put into a veſſell then it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: thus the holy Ghoſt was <hi>infuſed</hi> into the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>in Baptiſme,</hi> as namely to the making of them cleane both from originall, and all former actuall ſinnes. 2. <hi>Diffuſion</hi> is, when liquor is powred in ſo long, till no part of the veſſell bee left emptie; thus the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> was <hi>diffuſed</hi> into the Apoſtles after Chriſts reſurrection,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.23.</note> 
               <hi>when hee breathed vpon them</hi> and filled them as full (if I may ſo ſay) of the Spirit of God, as they were in the beginning of the Spirite of life: when beſides the remiſſion of their owne ſinnes receiued in Baptiſme, they could remit, and retaine other mens ſinnes <hi>miniſteria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter,</hi> as the Miniſters, and officers of God ordained for that purpoſe: <hi>Quorum remiſeritis peccata</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) Whoſoeuer ſinnes ye remit,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.23.</note> they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them: and whoſoeuer ſinnes ye retaine, they are retayned. 3. <hi>Effuſion</hi> is, when the veſſell
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15174:29"/> is ſo repleniſhed, that it runnes ouer againe, and may ſerue to be imparted to others. In this manner the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was <hi>effuſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> or powred out vpon the Apoſtles <hi>at the Pentecoſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſayth S. <hi>Paul) quem effudit,</hi> whom God powred out abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon vs;<note place="margin">Caietan. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>tam abundè</hi> (ſaith <hi>Caietan) vt in alios deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetur,</hi> ſo abundantly, that they could miniſterially, and by certaine effects giue him to others too: as when they not onely receiued the holy Ghoſt to worke mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, to ſpeake with tongues, &amp;c. but to giue that miraculous power to others likewiſe by their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; as alſo thoſe admirable effects, which attend <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> which haue <hi>euer beene giuen by the Apoſtles, and the Biſhops</hi> their ſucceſſors, ſince our Sauiours aſcenſion.</p>
            <p n="91">91 But to conclude this matter: the holy Ghoſt is giuen not onely in Baptiſme, and after that in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, &amp;c. but ſometimes alſo before Baptiſme (ſo that it cannot ſeeme to be tyed to it) as plainely appeares. Act. 10. For when <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion,<note place="margin">Act. 10.44. &amp; 46.</note> and his family were feruent with the heate of faith, and beleeued in God with all their hearts; the Holy Ghoſt fell on them, and they praiſed God with diuers tongues, and languages; which was before they were baptized by S. <hi>Peter:</hi> but as ſoone as it was euident, that the gift of the Holy Ghoſt was powred vpon them, <hi>Apoſtolica magiſteria,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>) the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. 76 ad Steph.</note> or the Apoſtolicke magiſtracie (which are now the Biſhops) <hi>per omnia diuini praecepti, atque E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelij legem ſeruabant,</hi> obſerued the Euangelicall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15174:30"/> law,<note place="margin">Act. 10.48.</note> and diuine precept in all things, both in bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and <hi>confirming</hi> thoſe Gentiles. And thus much is ſpoke by the way (yet much to our purpoſe) that no offence may be taken at the ſaying of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who wondered <hi>how Nouatus could haue the holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ l. 6. c. 42</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing he was neuer confirmed by the Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="92">92 And now <hi>Illuc vnde abij, redeo,</hi> I returne to my propoſed courſe, viz. to ſhew, that as the vſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation (according to the Church Hiſtorie) was continued by many particular chiefe Biſhops, ſo it hath beene likewiſe confirmed by many particular and famous Councels. I will paſſe ouer many later, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one or two of the more ancient: the former is <hi>Conciltum Elebertinum,</hi> the Councel of <hi>Eliberis,</hi> which was about the time of the firſt Nicene Councel. There we reade in the 38. Canon <hi>Fidelis aliquis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Can. 38.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. qui laua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum ſuum integrum habet,</hi> A Chriſtian, that hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit Baptiſme (I thinke it meanes <hi>Confirmation</hi> after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme) <hi>poſſe baptizare in neceſsitate infirmitatis poſitum Catechumenum,</hi> may baptize a new conuert in caſe of neceſſitie: but ſo that after Baptiſme, if the partie baptized recouer, <hi>Ad Epiſcopum eum perducat,</hi> hee muſt bring him to the Biſhop. And why ſo? <hi>vt per manus impoſitionem perfici poſsit,</hi> that by <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> hee might receiue <hi>perfection,</hi> as in thoſe daies it was called: <hi>not</hi> that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> ſhould <hi>receiue perfection</hi> thereby, <hi>but the baptized;</hi> which verie phraſe the Fathers ſometimes vſed, as alſo this Councell doth in the alledged Canon, and Canon 77. <hi>Si quis Diaconus regens plebem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Can: 77:</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If a Deacon
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15174:30"/> hauing cure of ſoules ſhall baptize any without a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Prieſt, <hi>Epiſcopus eos per benedictionem perficere debebit,</hi> the Biſhop muſt <hi>perfit</hi> them by his bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing, that is, <hi>by C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="93">93 My ſecond inſtance ſhall be in the Councell of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> held either in the time of <hi>Liberius,</hi> or of <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome:</hi> where we reade thus, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet baptizatos, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Laod. Can. 48.</note> They who are baptized muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue holy <hi>Chriſme,</hi> that is, <hi>Confirmation,</hi> (as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the circumſtances of that place) and become partakers of the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">Aug. trac. 118: in ſo. Euang.</note> This name of <hi>Chriſme</hi> both Counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, and Fathers giue to <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> but we vſe neither name, nor element, becauſe we finde neither in the booke of God.</p>
            <p n="94">94 From Hiſtorie, and <hi>Councels</hi> wee deſcend to <hi>Fathers,</hi> and in their writings we finde the vſe, and continuance of <hi>Confirmation</hi> very frequent, whether we conſult the Greeke, or Latine Fathers. We haue tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon diuers of them in this paſſage; it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice therefore now to vrge a place of Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe many of the circumſtances fit this preſent text and occaſion.</p>
            <p n="95">95 Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaking in the perſon of a Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerian, ſaith, <hi>An neſcis Eccleſiarum hunc eſſe morem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. ad verſ. Lucifer: c: 4.</note> 
               <hi>vt baptizatis poſtea manus imponantur?</hi> Knoweſt thou not, that it is the cuſtome of the Church after Baptiſme to vſe <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi> and to inuoke the H. Spirit for thoſe, that haue bin heretofore baptized? Will you haue authority for it?<note place="margin">Act: 8: and Act. 19.</note> Turne ouer the Acts of the Apoſtles (ſaith he) there is authority ſufficient:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15174:31"/> and yet if there were no text of Scripture for it, the conſent of the whole world in this caſe <hi>inſtar praecepti obtineret,</hi> were in ſtead of a precept, and ſufficient to approue it. And though this were the ſpeach of an hereticke concerning the practiſe of the Church in thoſe daies; yet the Orthodoxe, who beares the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part in the Dialogue, allowes of it, with a <hi>Non quidem abnuo,</hi> I deny not, but this is the cuſtome of the Church, that the Biſhops ride abroad to <hi>confirme,</hi> to <hi>Biſhop</hi> thoſe, who haue beene heretofore baptized by Prieſts,<note place="margin">Chemnit. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Concil. Trid. l. 2.</note> and Deacons. And <hi>Chemnitius</hi> ſpeaking of this cuſtome out of this place of Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> ſaith, that it was <hi>abſque dubio bona, &amp; vtilis conſuetudo,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt a good and profitable cuſtome. In like manner <hi>Cartwr.</hi>
               <note place="margin">T. C. p. 197.</note> in effect confeſſeth, that Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is very ancient, and that it hath beene well inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted; for he ſaith, that <hi>it now differeth, and is degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the firſt inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="96">96 This holy <hi>Canon,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of the Church hath continued inuiolable ſince the Primitiue times vntill our age, in all Churches, where the Hicrarchie of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops hath continued:<note place="margin">Theod. haeret. fab. l. 3. in Nouat.</note> onely I finde in <hi>Theodoret</hi> an obſeruation worthy the remembrance. The <hi>Nouatians</hi> (the Puritan heretickes <hi>of thoſe times</hi>) vſed not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;<note place="margin">Concil. Load. Can. 7:</note> and therefore the Fathers of the <hi>Laodicean</hi> Councell, enacted in their ſeuenth Canon, that all thoſe <hi>Nouatians,</hi> who returned to the Church, <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum fidei docerentur, et ſancto Chriſmate inungerentur,</hi> ſhould be taught the Creede, and then <hi>Confirmed,</hi> and ſo admitted to the holy Communion. Howeuer
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15174:31"/> then theſe Heretickes neglected Confirmation, yet if they returned to the Church, the Church euer made this Canon good vpon them, and <hi>confirmed</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="97">97 If Confirmation haue beene depraued, if it haue receiued any ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, or additions, from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wee renounce the abuſes, and reforme Confirmation (according to <hi>Caluins</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) to the firſt Apoſtolicall practiſe, and inſtitution,<note place="margin">Caluin. Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: l: 4. c: 19. §: 13 &amp; Comment. in Heb: 6.2.</note> that is to <hi>Prayer and Impoſition of hands.</hi> For there is no reaſon, why the holy, ancient, Eccleſiaſticall, Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical conſtitutions ſhould vtterly be aboliſhed for ſome abuſes crept in. By this heady prepoſterous courſe, the Church would rather become deformed, then refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; by this meanes we ſhould not haue ſo much as a Sacrament left vs.</p>
            <p n="98">98 When therefore ſome one, or other of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches</hi> (who haue pulled downe the Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracie of Biſhops, and haue erected the Anarchie of a confuſed lay-presbyterie, and ſo conſequently caſt off the ſacred vſe of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which <hi>cannot ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Biſhop</hi>) ſhal reſolutely tell vs (whom in this point, and many other they eſteeme no better then Papiſts) <hi>etiamſi vetuſtiſsimam hanc eſſe obſeruationem, &amp; multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſaeculorum conſenſu firmatam oſtendatis, nihil tamen efficitis,</hi> though this obſeruation and practiſe be neuer ſo ancient, though it be confirmed by the conſent and continuance of neuer ſo many ages, it is to little or no purpoſe; then <hi>cauete,</hi> take heed I pray you,<note place="margin">Aug. tract. 6. in Euang. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; excipite verba contradicentium reſpuenda, non tranſglutienda, et viſceribus danda,</hi> and entertaine theſe ſpeeches of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15174:32"/> Spirits, as words to be reiected, not to be chewed, much leſſe to be diſgeſted. Do as Chriſt did, when they offered him the bitter potion. He taſted it, and ſpit it out: ſo do you, Heare theſe words, &amp; loath them: and thus (it ſeemes) hath the <hi>Reformed Church of Bohemia done.</hi> For in that Church after Baptiſme <hi>gratiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Harmon. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. p. 94.</note> 
               <hi>quam Baptiſmus complectitur, impoſitione manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in ipſis teſtatam faciunt,</hi> the Gouernours of the Church teſtifie vnto the world by <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi> the grace which is giuen in Baptiſme: <hi>ad militia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidei eos confirmant,</hi> (marke, I beſeech you) they confirme, ſtrengthen, and arme them for the warfare of faith; and ſo in a conuenient, and holy manner, by the vſe of pure, and ſignificant ceremonies <hi>ad Sacramentum coenae domini adducunt,</hi> they bring them to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: which is one, and the ſame practiſe with the Church of England; as you may ſee it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet downe by way of Canon, or Conſtitution in the Booke of <hi>Common Prayer:</hi> where wee reade, that <hi>None ſhall bee admitted to the holy Communion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Common prayer booke.</note> 
               <hi>vntil ſuch time, as he can ſay the Catechiſme, and be confirmed.</hi> This is the <hi>conſtitution of the Church of England</hi> (I ſay) <hi>and confirmed by Act of Parliament</hi> with the reſt of the Booke, and ſtands in full force ſtill, if it ſhould pleaſe our Prelates to exact it. If you require <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie</hi> for it, we ſhall finde this <hi>Canon as ancient as Saint Auſtine;</hi> for hee tels vs, that this was <hi>dogma Eccleſiaſticum,</hi> an Eccleſiaſticall Canon in his time, <hi>Manus impoſitione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. dogmat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Chriſmate communiti, Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtiae myſterijs admittantur:</hi> Let thoſe, who are
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15174:32"/> 
               <hi>confirmed by Impoſition of hands,</hi> be admitted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſed Euchariſt. And this Canon we haue ſeene approoued,<note place="margin">Concil. Laod, Can. 7.</note> and confirmed by the Councell of <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">99 So then neither we, nor this <hi>Reformed Church of Bohemia</hi> borrow this practiſe of Confirmation (as ſome falſely giue forth) from the Papiſts, or Popiſh decretalls, no;<note place="margin">T. C. l. 1. p. 199</note> but as our Communion Booke truly ſayes,<note place="margin">Common prayer Booke.</note> 
               <hi>It is agreeable with the vſage of the Church in times paſt.</hi> This was the cuſtome of the olde, the Primitiue Church,<note place="margin">Tertul aduerſ. valent. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>leſia authenticae regulae ſic tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it,</hi> the Church of the ancient, and authenticke rule held thus, and thus hold we. <hi>Tertullian</hi> thought this a ſufficient anſwere to ſtoppe the mouth of <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> that groſſe giddie Hereticke: and the Church of Bohemia labouring to preuent all obiections giues this reaſon onely for her doings,<note place="margin">Harmon. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. p. 94.</note> 
               <hi>Huius rei in prima Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia indicia, atque exempla etiam extant manifeſta,</hi> there are manifold teſtimonies, and examples of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion yet extant in the Primitiue Church. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome ſay, that the practiſe of the Primitiue Church is nothing to vs, vnleſſe we proue it out of Scripture; the ſame Church of Bohemia auerres,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that <hi>Prima Eccleſia eſt poſterorum vera, &amp; optima magiſtra, et praecundo ducit nos,</hi> the Primitiue Church is the true and moſt excellent Miſtreſſe of all later Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and leades vs the way; and wee may fafely follow her, for ſhe followed the Apoſtles ſteppes, and borrowed this practiſe from my Text; as before
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15174:33"/> I noted out of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="100">100. If their authoritie be denyed, and ſome new-fangled interpretations bee lately fancied, framed, and receiued by a few vaine-glorious noueliſts, to make voide the honour and priuiledge proper to the <hi>Biſhops, (the Fathers, and Gouernors of the Church,)</hi> whom they would ſhoulder out, &amp; with them almoſt all good order: the queſtion muſt no longer be, <hi>Whether Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation bee found in Scripture;</hi> but, <hi>Whether the ancient Fathers</hi> of the Primitiue Church were more likely to interpret the Scriptures truly, or ſome late Noueliſts; who to maintaine ſome odde fancies of their owne braine, haue forged new and ſtrange gloſſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to Antiquitie, the vnderſtanding of Fathers, and other Reformed Churches; for thoſe Churches, that follow <hi>Luthers</hi> reformation, vſe <hi>Confirmation</hi> with ſo many of theſe circumſtances, as that Diſcipline can admit.</p>
            <p n="101">101 Certainely our Church hath taken the ſafer courſe; for we profeſſe <hi>manente forma (Confirmationis) in ſuo ordine,</hi> ſo long as that forme and order of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> is obſerued, and no other, then was vſed in the Apoſtles times, and by the Apoſtles themſelues, <hi>quantumlibet quaerant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de Praeſcript. c. 14.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; tractent, &amp; omnem libidinem curioſitatis effundant</hi> (to vſe <hi>Tertul.</hi> phraſe) let their braines work, and their teeming wits bring forth ſome rare inuentions, ſuch as were neuer heard of, neuer dreamed of before, ſuch as may diſcouer their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious itching curioſities: yet (we hope) the Church of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15174:33"/> England will, as hitherto it hath, euer continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the ſame courſe; wee doubt not, but it will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitate the practiſe, and embrace the enterpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe ancients, who, by the confeſſion of the whole Church of God, were <hi>gratia ſcientiae donati,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with an extraordinary grace, and gift of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to vnderſtand, and interpret the will of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="102">102. For as there was in the law before Chriſt <hi>liber Propheticus</hi> (as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> cals it) the booke of the Law and the Prophets,<note place="margin">Ambr. de Fide ad Gratianum l. 3. c. 7.</note> which contained the types and propheſies of Chriſt, which booke was <hi>ſignatus</hi> ſealed vp ſo firmely at that time; that neither Elders, nor Powers, nor Angels, nor Archangels durſt offer to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold it, the prerogatiue of opening, and explayning it being reſerued onely to Chriſt himſelfe: ſo was there alſo in the primitiue times ſucceeding Chriſt, <hi>Liber Sacerdotalis,</hi> that is the Scriptures, and the receiued ſence of Scriptures penned by the Fathers, Doctors; and Biſhops in their ſeuerall ages, of ſo great authority in the Church, that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaking of them ſayth, <hi>Quis noſtrum reſignare audeat?</hi> What man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs is ſo hardy, as to offer violence vnto them? Who dares breake open thoſe Seales, or infringe the credite and authority of this <hi>Sacerdotall booke,</hi> ſeeing it was <hi>ſignatus à confeſſoribus, &amp; multorum iam martyrio conſecratus</hi> ſigned by the reuerend confeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and ſealed vp with the blood of many a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Martyr?</p>
            <p n="103">103. And yet after ſo many hundred yeares, behold
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15174:34"/> there was one of late amongſt vs, who aduentured himſelfe ſo farre, as to confront the Fathers in this doctrine,<note place="margin">T. C. l. 1. p. 119. &amp; l. 3. p. 232.</note> to oppoſe his fancie againſt the iudgement of the Church, to call the practiſe of the Apoſtles into queſtion, to ſet a new conſtruction, a ſtrange gloſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a manifeſt text: that ſo he might raſe out a <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall point of religion,</hi> wherein both Fathers, and Church, and Apoſtles, and Scriptures haue agreed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with one ioynt conſent for fifteen or ſixteen hundreth yeares together. If any man be left amongſt vs of his temper, or rather of his diſtemper, I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay to this <hi>new-bred doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Valent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> what <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes to <hi>Valentinus</hi> new brood of Gods, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Whether it be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I know not well my ſelfe, for I am much in doubt, whether I ſhould more <hi>wonder</hi> at their pride, or laugh at their folly.</p>
            <p n="104">
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.16.</note>104 Sure I am, <hi>Non habemus talem conſuetudinem, nec Eccleſiae Dei,</hi> We haue no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Chuches of God, nor may we (I pray God) euer grow to that height of madneſſe, as to preferre our owne fond conceits before the practiſe of the Apoſtles, the conſent of Fathers, and cuſtome of the Church. We deſire to be of no <hi>new cut,</hi> but with the Fathers of the Firſt Nicene Councell,<note place="margin">Concil. Nicen Can. 7.</note> our prayers are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the old cuſtome may ſtand, that it may euer preuaile.</p>
            <p n="105">105 Seeing then <hi>Confirmation</hi> is of ſuch <hi>Antiquity</hi> in the Church of God, that it hath the vniuerſall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church, Fathers, Councels, Apoſtles, and Scripture text it ſelfe to grace, to vphold, to ſettle it in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15174:34"/> the Church, let vs honor <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Confirmation;</hi> let vs haue them in that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which we owe, and they deſerue; and deſire of God, that they may euer continue of full force, to the glory of God, and the good of his Church.</p>
            <p n="106">106 I ſhould paſſe on to the parts euſuing, but (I feare) I haue beene too too troubleſome already; and I ſhall haue diuers occaſions to ſpeake of the other parts, euery one of them being ſufficient to yeeld mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a ſeuerall Sermon: but leſt I ſhould ſeeme to leaue vnperfect, what in my diuiſion I propoſed, may it pleaſe you to perfect the other circumſtances out of that, whieh hath beene ſpoke; for from thence may be deduced ſufficient proofe for the remainder of my text.</p>
            <p n="107">107 The next point I obſerued, were the <hi>Miniſters of Confirmation, Apoſtoli, Apoſtles</hi> they were,<note place="margin">2. part.</note> and their ſucceſſors the Biſhops and no other. So you heard from <hi>Clement Epiſt.</hi> 3. Saint <hi>Cyprian Epiſt.</hi> 73. <hi>Cornelius apud Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <hi>Melchiades Can,</hi> 2. de Conſecr. Diſt. 5. <hi>Concil. Eleber. Can.</hi> 38, Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ.</hi> in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. Saint <hi>Ierome aduer. Lucifer. c.</hi> 4. Saint <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil.</hi> 18. in Act. Apoſt. Saint <hi>Auſt. de Trin. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 26. And <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 42. in Non. Teſt. <hi>Leo Epiſt.</hi> 37. <hi>c.</hi> 2 <hi>Caluin. inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. §. 4.</p>
            <p n="108">108 And <hi>S. Ierome</hi> giues a good reaſon,<note place="margin">Hieron, aduerſ. Lucifer. c. 4. Bucer. in Eph. 4 Tract. Quid fit Eccleſ.</note> why the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are the <hi>only Miniſters</hi> of this bleſſed action. The power of this bleſſing (ſaith he) is giuen to the <hi>Biſhops only, in honore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacerdotii</hi> for the honor of their Prelacy: &amp; fitly (ſaith <hi>Bucer</hi>) do <hi>the Biſhops only confirm vs</hi> in our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15174:35"/> Faith, ſince vnto the Biſhops is committed the chiefe care of the Church: and ſo conſequently the mayne charge of our ſoules. And if <hi>Confirmation</hi> be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who ſo fit to confer it, as the chiefe of Prieſts?</p>
            <p n="109">109 The third circumſtance was, <hi>the Perſons</hi> that were <hi>Confirmed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. part.</note> 
               <hi>ſuper illos</hi> vpon them. And who are theſe, that are capable of Confirmation? ſurely ſuch onely as are baptiſed. This was the cuſtome (you heard of the Apoſtles <hi>Act.</hi> 8. and <hi>Act.</hi> 19. <hi>to confirme thoe onely that were baptiſed:</hi> and the whole Church hath euer ſince carefully obſerued the ſame practiſe, as you haue ſeene ſufficiently manifeſted by Saint <hi>Clem.</hi> Epiſt. 3. <hi>Tertul. de Baptiſmo.</hi> cap. 6. &amp; 8. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Epiſt. 73. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> in Heb. 6. <hi>Ierom.</hi> aduer. Lucifer. cap. 4. <hi>Auſt. quaeſt.</hi> 42. in N. Teſt. <hi>Emiſſ.</hi> Homil. in Pentecoſt. <hi>Coucil, Laod.</hi> Can. 48. <hi>Bohem. Confeſſ.</hi> p. 94,</p>
            <p n="110">
               <note place="margin">4 part.</note>110 My fourth obſeruation was the <hi>forme,</hi> and that is <hi>Prayer and Impoſition of hands:</hi> my text tels you ſo much: and the practiſe of the Church hath euer retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this forme. <hi>No bleſsing</hi> is beſtowed at any time in &amp; by the church <hi>without prayer,</hi> neither is the H. ghoſt giuen <hi>ad robur</hi> to <hi>confirme</hi> vs (I ſpeake of the ordinary meanes) without <hi>Impoſition of hands.</hi> For this you haue had good euidence, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. and <hi>Act.</hi> 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>Clem.</hi> Ep. 3. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de Bapt. cap. 8. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Epiſt. 73. <hi>Melchiad.</hi> Can. 2. de Conſecr. Diſt. 5. <hi>Concil. Eleber.</hi> Can. 38. <hi>Ierome</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Lucifer. c. 4. <hi>Auſt.</hi> quaeſt. 42. in Nou. Teſtament. And <hi>Auſt.</hi> (or <hi>Gennadius</hi>) de Eccle. dogmat. c. 52. <hi>Leo</hi> Epiſt. 37. <hi>Confeſ. Bohem.</hi> p. 94. <hi>Caluin.</hi> Inſtit. l. 4. c. 19. §. 4 &amp; Comment. in Heb. 6.2.</p>
            <p n="111">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:15174:35"/>111. The <hi>effect</hi> (which is my laſt part) is the <hi>receiuing the holy Ghoſt in obſignatorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Part. Eraſ Sancer. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Marlor. in Act. Apoſt. 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; confirmatorem</hi> (as <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Sarcerius</hi> ſaith) to ſeale our religion, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs in the true faith, and feare of Chriſt: beſides many other gifts, and graces (as he affirmeth) of the holy Ghoſt, which we receiue in Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="112">112 This the Fathers (it ſeemes) conſidered,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Bap. c. 8.</note> and therfore they had this bleſſing in ſo high and reuerent eſtimation, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that by this bleſſing the hand doth <hi>inuite,</hi> and call downe the holy Ghoſt: and this being done, <hi>ſanctiſsimus ſpiritus ſuper emun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data, et benedicta corpora libens deſcendit,</hi> the holy ghoſt deſcends willingly vpon thoſe cleanſed and bleſſed bodies; <hi>cleanſed</hi> (by baptiſme) and <hi>bleſſed</hi> (by Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation): and in his book <hi>de Praeſcriptionibus</hi> he tels vs,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Prae. c. 36.</note> that the Church by this meanes doth <hi>cloth</hi> vs with the holy Spirit; as before you heard. Neither is this to be vnderſtood of an outward <hi>clothing,</hi> no; <hi>Infunditur</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>) hee is <hi>powred</hi> into vs,<note place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. 73. ad Iubai.</note> and hee is <hi>powred</hi> after a plenteous manner, <hi>Infunditur ſuper, in</hi> and <hi>vpon</hi> vs, inſide and outſide, both ſoule and body are made partakers of this admirable bleſſing.<note place="margin">Ric de Sto: Vic. ſer de ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. ſancto.</note> Yet leſt the holy Ghoſt may ſeeme to be giuen in Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>infuſiue</hi> onely (according to the ſchoole diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in ſome ſmall meaſure, <hi>Tertul.</hi> tels vs, that he is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>effuſiue, abundantly in Confirmation:</hi> his words are theſe,
<q>
                  <l>Signari populos, effuſo pignore ſancto,<note place="margin">Tertul aduer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Marc. l. 1. Cat. c. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mirandae virtutis opus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The people being ſigned, or <hi>confirmed, the holy Ghoſt</hi> is <hi>powred out abundantly</hi> vpon them, which is a worke of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15174:36"/> maruellous <hi>vertue.</hi> And fitly doth <hi>Tertullian</hi> terme it a worke of <hi>vertue,</hi> or <hi>power,</hi> ſince Chriſt promiſeth his Apoſtles, that they ſhall receiue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Act. 18.</note> the <hi>power</hi> of the Spirit, (as we reade); and and <hi>Leo</hi> profeſſeth that by Epiſcopall Impoſition of hands <hi>virtus ſpiritus confertur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo Epiſt. 37. c. 2.</note> the <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the Spirit is beſtowed. Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> therefore ſaith, that the Apoſtles had the holy Ghoſt before <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug tract 74. in Euan. Ioh.</note> but they had him <hi>minus</hi> in a leſſe manner, where as in <hi>Confirmation</hi> he (that is his gifts) was giuen them <hi>amplius</hi> in a larger meaſure: becauſe Confirmation added to the former grace by ſtrengthning and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it.</p>
            <p n="112">112 This doctrine the very letter of the text affords vs; for if it pleaſe you to conferre the places, where Chriſt giues, and where he promiſeth the holy Ghoſt, you will acknowledge (I am perſwaded) a great difference in the manner, and meaſure of beſtowing the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Behold <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. Chriſt ſayd to his Apoſtles, <hi>Accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.22.</note> there he giues them the holy ghoſt: and yet after this he makes promiſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. that they ſhall receiue the holy ghoſt.<note place="margin">Act 1.8.</note> There <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> receiue; here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ye ſhall receiue: there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, receiue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit; here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he makes promiſe, that they ſhall receiue, not only the Spirit, which they had receiued before but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the power of the Spirit, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>virtutem ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſuperuenientis,</hi> the power of the Spirit, not onely coming <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon you (the Apoſtles), but <hi>ſuperue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientis coming vpon</hi> (as it were) to bee an addition to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15174:36"/> thoſe gifts, and graces, which they had before: which is excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly expreſſed by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Firſt, <hi>the power of the Spirit</hi> is giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who had the Spirit before: and ſecondly, the ſpirit doth <hi>ſuperuenire come vpon,</hi> and make an addition to his former gifts, and thereby giues an encreaſe of grace, and a greater power, then they had before: for (as it is obſerued) the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſometimes <hi>violentiae ſignificationem incluſam habet,</hi> hath violence, or power included in it;<note place="margin">Scapula.</note> and the word is ſeldom vſed in the New Teſtament, but where it denotate a greater power, a more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall gift then was giuen before: or rather an additon to a former gift. As namely, when that great promiſe is made to the bleſſed Virgin, it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Luc. 1.35.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the holy Ghoſt ſhall come down vpon thee, and yet (without doubt) ſhee had the holy ghoſt before, for by the Angels report ſhe was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ful of grace before, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luc. 1.28.</note> the Lord was with her: but now the holy Ghoſt was to <hi>come downe</hi> vpon her, and vpon the former gifts in a greater meaſure, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuperueniet,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſuper te,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 1.35. &amp; Act. 1. 8.</note> two <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, two <hi>ſuper's</hi> in both places, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer comes along with both, in both; to ſhew, that the holy Ghoſt was to <hi>come downe</hi> in greater power, and for a more powerfull effect, then hee came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, not onely to come downe <hi>ſuper eos</hi> vpon them, but <hi>ſuperuenire</hi> to come vpon his former graces with a new ſupply.</p>
            <p n="113">113 And therefore <hi>Luc.</hi> 11. wee finde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:15174:37"/> vſed, where it is manifeſt, that a greater power came vpon the former with a kinde of violence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luc 11.22.</note> though a ſtrong man holds poſſeſſion, yet when a ſtronger then he <hi>comes vpon him,</hi> hee will conquer him, and take his poſſeſſion from him. Thus the caſe ſtands between oppoſites; but where the ſame ſpirit beſtowes his gifts, and does <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuperuenire,</hi> come vpon the former, and ſo come vpon them, <hi>vt accipiant virtutem ſpiritus,</hi> that they, who had the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſhould now haue the <hi>power of the Spirit,</hi> hee doth not only ſettle and confirme his former gifts in them, but he beſtowes vpon them more powerfull gifts then they had before. Which may not be vnderſtood, as though this <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>powerfull gifts</hi> of the ſpirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted onely in ſpeaking of tongues, working of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp;c. (as ſome would haue it); but the ſpirit was giuen them chiefly to bee <hi>Paracletus</hi> their <hi>Comforter,</hi> to confirme them in the true faith, &amp; ſo to ſtrengthen them, that they might ſtoutly reſiſt temptations, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantedly paſſe thorough perſecutions, and conſtantly beare witneſſe of Chriſt, and his bleſſed actions: as may be ſeene,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 1.2.3 Io. 14 16.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. and for this ende, and purpoſe is he promiſed to continue with vs to the end of the world. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14 Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> therefore ſpeaking of theſe two ſeuerall giuings of the holy Ghoſt, affordes vs this good obſeruation.<note place="margin">Cyril Hieroſ. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>heſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Nunc accipite ex parte, tunc accipietis perfecte,</hi> Chriſt fayth <hi>Iohn</hi> the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth: Receiue now the holy Ghoſt <hi>in part,</hi> but <hi>Acts</hi> 1, he promiſeth, that they ſhall receiue him <hi>perfectly</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:15174:37"/> and hence (it may be) from this perfect manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the holy Ghoſt, is <hi>Confirmation called perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and they, that haue receiued Confirmation, are ſtyled <hi>perfit Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="114">114 Will you know then the benefits which we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue by <hi>Confirmation,</hi> by this <hi>effuſion</hi> of the holy Ghoſt, and his vertue? 1. <hi>Animae ſpiritu illuminatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. carnis c. 8.</note> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi>) The ſoule is enlightned by the holy Spirit. 2. (as before you heard) <hi>Sancto ſpiritu veſtitur,</hi> the ſoule is cloathed with the holy Spirit. <hi>Tertul. de Praeſcript. c.</hi> 36. which is the ſame with <hi>induebantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24.49:</note> when the Apoſtles were confirmed at the Pentecoſt. 3. The ſoule receiues <hi>augmentum ad gratiam,</hi> encreaſe to grace. <hi>Melchiad.</hi> Can. 2. de Conſecr. Diſt. 5. &amp; <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſen.</hi> Homil. in Pentecoſt. 4. <hi>Confirmatur ad pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> (ſo <hi>Melchiad.</hi> Ib. &amp; <hi>Emiſſ.</hi> Ib.) it is confirmed for battell; that is (as the <hi>Bohem. Confeſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bohem. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. p. 94.</note> expreſſeth it) <hi>ad militiam fidei,</hi> for the battell, or warfare of faith. Not to liue at variance amongſt our brethren, or quarrell about religion. 5. therefore Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that one branch of this ſtrengthning is <hi>confirmatio vnitatis in Eccleſia Chriſti,</hi> to ſtrengthen vs againſt the enemie,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Heb. 6.</note> and to confirme vs in the vnitie of the Church of Chriſt. 6, By this meanes (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine) cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus diuina charitas inſpiratur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug de Bapt. cont. Donat. l. 3. c. 16.</note> diuine charitie is inſpired into our hearts and ſoules. And finally, (as that anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Authour bearing the name of <hi>Clement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clem Epiſt. 3:</note> ſaith) <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templici Spiritus gratia confirmamur,</hi> we are comforted, and confirmed with the ſeuen-fold grace, with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gifts of the holy Spirit; which are the gifts, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15174:38"/> entreates God to encreaſe in vs, before he layes his hands vpon vs: as you may ſee in the <hi>Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Booke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="115">115 So then (it ſeemes) by Confirmation we receiue the eſpeciall gifts,<note place="margin">Leo Epiſt. 37. c. 2. Leoni E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo Rauen.</note> and (as <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith) the <hi>vertue of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and if it be ſo, that we receiue ſo many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, ſuch <hi>vertue</hi> by Confirmation, wee may ceaſe wondering why Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Cypr Epiſt. 73 Concil Eleb. can. 38. Clem. Epiſt. 3.</note> that wee are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated;</hi> and the Councell of <hi>Eliberis,</hi> that we are <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited</hi> by Confirmation: &amp; no maruell then, if S. <hi>Clement</hi> vpon this conſideration affirm that <hi>without Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation we cannot become perfit Chriſtians.</hi> For, if by Confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſoules are <hi>enlightned</hi> &amp; <hi>clothed</hi> with the H. ſpirit: if by Confirmation we <hi>receiue grace,</hi> and are <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> againſt the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations of the enemy; if by Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wee are ſetled, and <hi>confirmed in the vnitie of the Church, and heauenly charitie is inſpired into our ſoules;</hi> if we <hi>receiue the ſeuenfold grace of the holy Spirit</hi> in Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; if this be the <hi>publike, and ordinarie meanes</hi> (for ought we know) to procure theſe bleſſings from God; then muſt we needs acknowledge, that we reape much <hi>perfection by</hi> &amp; <hi>in Confirmation,</hi> &amp; we haue great cauſe to deſire, and ſeek after Confirmation, that ſo we may be <hi>clothed</hi> with theſe perfections.</p>
            <p n="116">116 And that we may not doubt, but that <hi>this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect doth follow Impoſition of hands,</hi> marke what eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>Caluin</hi> affords vs. <hi>Preces ſequitur manuum impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio,</hi> After prayer followes <hi>Impoſition of hands;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (ſaith he) the Apoſtles teſtifie, that the grace of the Spirit is not included in the externall <hi>Ceremonie;</hi> and yet they neglect not this <hi>Ceremonie,</hi> which was giuen
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15174:38"/> them <hi>diuinitus</hi> from God aboue, for this end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (viz. for the beſtowing this effect:<note place="margin">Caluin. in Act. Apoſt. 8.17.</note>) <hi>&amp; quia non temere vſurpant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſimul annexus eſt effectus,</hi> and becauſe they vſe it aduiſedly, <hi>the effect is annexed to the Ceremonie.</hi> And then he concludes the point thus. <hi>Haec ſignorum eſt vtilitas &amp; efficacia, quod in illis Deus opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; tamen vnus manet gratiae autor,</hi> this is the benefit, and effect of ſignes (or Ceremonies) that God workes in them, and yet there is but <hi>one Author of grace,</hi> God himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="117">117 Thus you ſee, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue proued, what I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, by the Catholicke, the generall conſent of graue Antiquitie. If any man reprehend me, as if I <hi>erred</hi> in this point, <hi>patiatur me (quaeſo) errare cum talibus,</hi> I muſt entreate him in S. <hi>Ieromes</hi> wordes,<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> that he would giue me leaue to <hi>erre</hi> with ſuch men as theſe; <hi>&amp; cum me er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is mei multos ſocios habere perſpexerit, ipſe veritatis ſuae ſaltem vnum (antiquum) aſtipulatorem proferre debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> and ſince he ſeeth me to haue ſo many companions of my <hi>error,</hi> fit it is, that he bring forth at leaſt one <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> maintainer of his <hi>truth.</hi> But ſurely he (who euer he be) is ſo farre from it, that if you will ſtand to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Antiquitie, <hi>veritas nobis adiucabitur,</hi> the truth muſt needs be adiudged to vs, to be on our ſides, <hi>qui in ea regula incedimus, quam Eccleſia ab Apoſtolis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul de Praeſcript. c. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtoli a Chriſto, Chriſtus a Deo tradidit,</hi> who proceed conſtantly according to that rule, which the Church deliuered from the Apoſtles, the Apoſtles from Chriſt, and Chriſt from God.</p>
            <p n="118">118 <hi>Conſtat itaque ratio propoſiti noſtri,</hi> the reaſon
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15174:39"/> therfore of our propoſed diſcourſe ſtands firme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we proue, that <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> ought euer to be reteined in the Church of God; from whoſe hands mediatly we receiue ſo great gifts and bleſſings of the holy Ghoſt; without which bleſſed gifts (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>) wee can neither loue Chriſt, nor keep his commandements; both which we are able to do <hi>tanto minus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 74. in Euang. Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>quanto illum percipimus minus, &amp; tanto amplius quanto illum percipimus amplius,</hi> ſo much the leſſe, by how much leſſe wee receiue the holy Ghoſt, and ſo much the more by how much we receiue him the more, by the meanes of our <hi>Baptiſme, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Euchariſt,</hi> and other ſacred myſteries, whereby the gifts and graces of the holy Spirit are daily giuen, &amp; encreaſed in vs: whereof God grant, that we may all labour to become worthy partakers, to our <hi>Comfort,</hi> and his glorie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord; to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, &amp;c. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15174:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
